<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Munition against mans misery and mortality A treatice containing the most effectual remedies against the miserable state of man in this life, selected out of the chiefest both humane and divine authors; by Richard Smyth preacher of Gods word in Barstaple in Devonshire.</title>
            <author>Smyth, Richard, preacher in Barnstaple, Devonshire.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 203 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12558</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22878</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100020</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835875</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835875</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12558)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1531:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Munition against mans misery and mortality A treatice containing the most effectual remedies against the miserable state of man in this life, selected out of the chiefest both humane and divine authors; by Richard Smyth preacher of Gods word in Barstaple in Devonshire.</title>
                  <author>Smyth, Richard, preacher in Barnstaple, Devonshire.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[18] 136 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MVNITION A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GAINST MANS <hi>MISERY AND MORTALITY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> TREATICE CONTAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the moſt effectuall remedies againſt the miſerable ſtate of man in this life, ſelected out of the chiefeſt both humane and divine authors;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> RICHARD SMYTH <hi>preacher of Gods word in Barſtaple in Devonſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Edition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Ioſeph Barnes. 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:102:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull the Lady ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH BASSET, his ſingular good Lady, RI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHARD SMYTH hartily wiſheth all happineſſe in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N reading of Authors either divine or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, Deare Madame, men haue ever propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to themſelues diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent endes according as they haue beene diverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected; which is not to bee wondred at, ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">Senee ep. 109.</note> the moſt ſage heathen, ſith in one and the ſame meddow the oxe ſeekes graſſe, the dogge a hare, the ſtorke a ſnake or lizard.<note n="b" place="margin">Bernard. in Cantie. ſerm. 36.</note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> the beſt author that lived in ſo bad a time, reduceth theſe endes to fiue. There are, ſaith he, ſome that deſire to know only that they might knowe, and this is fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy curioſity; and there are ſome that deſire to knowe that they themſelues might bee knowne, and this is filthy vanity; and there are ſome that deſire to knowe that they may
<pb facs="tcp:102:3"/>ſell their knowledge, and this is filthie gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe, and there are ſome that deſire to knowe that they may edifie others and this is charitie, and there are ſome that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſire to knowe that they themſelues may bee edified, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd this is wiſdome. So that of theſe fiue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndes of knowledge onely the two latter are commendable, namely, when we covet know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge either to better our ſelues or others in vertue and pietie. Which two endes for my owne part I haue through Gods grace ever principally intended in the courſe of my poor ſtudies, ſeriouſly conſidering with my ſelfe how vaine even the lawfull knowledge of al other things is without the knowledge of thoſe things which concerne our owne wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and happineſſe: which your Ladyſhippe may finde expreſſed with profitable parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularitie in the ſecond ſection of the firſt Chapter of this Treatiſe. Now becauſe there is nothing the knowledge whereof ſo neerely toucheth vs as of our miſery, and true and effectuall remedies againſt our miſery, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue I in theſe my firſt labors publiſhed in print made choice of that argument, not only to edifie others, but alſo to edifie my ſelfe, and to haue in a readineſſe neceſſarie antidots and preſervatiues againſt ſuch croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as I both heretofore haue felt, and alſo muſt feele ſtill as long as my habitation is in
<pb facs="tcp:102:3"/>this vale of teares. Touching the manner of my handling this ſo important a ſubiect I may ſay as<note n="c" place="margin">Iuſt Lipſ. Politic. in prooemio.</note> a great Scholler of theſe times ſaid of a worke of his of another nature, that all things in this Treatiſe are mine, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing mine: all things mine in regard of the collection and diſpoſition of them, &amp; nothing mine in regard of the things the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, which I haue taken out of others, or at leaſt very little mine. I held this courſe beſt for ſundry reaſons which I cannot but impart to your good Ladyſhip. Firſt hereby I laid a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty vpon my ſelfe to ranke and put in order my beſt obſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in reading both humane and divine authors concerning theſe two ſo materiall points before ſpecified, namely ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s miſerie, and his reliefe. Secondly diſtruſting myne owne ſufficiencie to handle any matter laudable out of mine owne meditations, I thought it good to make my ſelfe beholden to others, whoſe names &amp; credit could not but procure authoritie to the worke and ſtir vp attention in the readers. Thirdly forasmuch as it is impoſſible for a man to avoid concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and coincidence both of notions and tearmes with others that haue written long before, which in this malignant age of ours might breed ſuſpicion both of theft &amp; vaine glory, as if I had robbed others of their medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and would deriue the praiſe thereof
<pb facs="tcp:102:4"/>to my ſelfe, I haue therefore alleaged the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors themſelues where I needed not, in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many things which mine owne thoughts ſuggeſted vnto me. As for the ſtile, ſaving where I tie my ſelfe to the words of others, it is plaine and familiar without pompe, art, or affectation, which I naturally as much abhor as any man living: and that ſpecially in ſuch an argument as this, where I labor to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort my ſelfe and others againſt the two maine branches of mans miſerie, the evils of paine, and the evils of fault, that is, the evils we ſuffer, and the evils which we doe, ſinne, and the puniſhments for ſinne.<note n="d" place="margin">Fab. Quin tilian. Inſtit Orator. lib. 9 c. 3. &amp; l. 11. cap. 1.</note> The verie heathen Orator hath wiſely obſerved that they are altogether vnworthy of mercy, that can talke arteficially of their miſery: &amp;<note n="c" place="margin">Arnob. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Gentes lib. 1.</note> a Chriſtian author well ſaith, that when wee deale in matters that cannot ſtand with af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectation &amp; oſtentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is, that admit no floriſhes of art, vnleſſe men will bewray pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable both abſurdity and hypocriſie, we muſt regard what is ſaid, not with what delight it is ſaid. For it is an argument of too vaine and wanton a mind to ſeeke for pleaſure in earneſt and important matters. Now as for the reaſons that haue moved me to dedicate theſe meditations to your Ladyſhippe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing muſt be ſaid thereof, I am not ignorant that men in the dedications of their labours
<pb facs="tcp:102:4"/>are led with ſundry and very different re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; ſome intend the eternizing of their fame and memorie to whome they dedicate their writings, as we read of that intolerable arrogant <hi>Appion</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Plinius na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. hiſt. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat ad Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſian.</note> who was wont to brag that he made all them immortall to whome he vouchſafed to intitle any of his books. But as for this benefit, nether doth your Ladyſhip eſteeme it, whoſe thoughts are not confined within the compaſſe of this world were it eternall, nor can I beſtow it, being ſo meane and obſcure, that it were madneſſe in me to thinke that I could ennoble others by anie monuments of mine, although otherwiſe wiſh, I were as able to doe it, as I know your Ladiſhip worthy thereof, &amp; that as he<note n="g" place="margin">Sen ep 23</note> ſaith of <hi>Pomponius Atticus, Cicero's</hi> letters will not ſuffer the name of <hi>Articus</hi> to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, ſo it were in my power to perpetuate your memorie. Others by their dedications hope to extort ſome benevolence or gift from their benefactors, neede beeing, if I may ſo ſpeake, the fatall penance of moſt Schollers. And indeed<note n="h" place="margin">Gulielmus Xylander as Lewen Clai. us re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orts praefat. in Dionem a ſe editum.</note> a worthie Scholler of our time (an eternall blot and reproach to the time) confeſſed to a friend of his, that famine not fame had cauſed him to publiſh divers of his workes But neither was this any motiue with me herein, ſith your ingenuous bounty towards my ſelfe, and others (ſo farre as your
<pb facs="tcp:102:5"/>intricated and diſtracted ſtate will permit) is ſo open that it rather needs reſtraint then provocation, or excitation, and for my owne particular, it hath ever beene far beyond not only my deſert, but alſo my deſire. But to come to the more ordinary endes of ſuch dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they are principally three, comfort, honor duty, or rather diſcharge of duty, all which I confeſſe, haue prevailed with me, in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of theſe my ſlender diſcourſes vnto your Lady ſhip. Many haue not only dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their writings, but directed their whole Treatiſes to ſuch as they deſired to comfort, as<note n="i" place="margin">Plutarch. conſolat ad Apollonium</note> 
               <hi>Plutarch,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Senee con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolat. ad Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyb. Abin. Martiam.</note> 
               <hi>Seneca,</hi> and others. Now this Treatiſe of mine, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding only to comfort vs in generall againſt all miſery, wherevnto our life in this fraile and tranſitory world is ſubiect, I haue dedicated the ſame to your Ladyſhip, that if it afford any vſe of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, your Ladiſhip might principally haue the benefitte thereof, whoſe almoſt inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable croſſes yea without great meaſure of grace, meerely inſupportable, ſtand not a little in need thereof: I muſt in diſcreation o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit particulars, which are to well knowne to them that know you, &amp; your ſtate. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whereas many in their dedications, as much as in them lie, ſeek to honor their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues to whom they intitle their works, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that I haue here in much reſpected the
<pb facs="tcp:102:5"/>ſame, in behalfe of your Ladiſhip. For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving beene a long time an eye witneſſe of your vertuous and religious converſation, &amp; occaſionally as it were enforced to take no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tice of the manifold and excellent graces of God ſhining in you, I could not but moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly imbrace any opportunitie to giue ſome publike teſtimonie therevnto, and a fitter could not occur then the publiſhing of this Treatiſe. And yet here I muſt doe you wrong by omitting particulars, who of your exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue modeſtie would hold your ſelfe wronged if I ſhould in particular giue you but your due praiſes, and ſpecifie your moſt eminent vertues. I therefore rather chuſe to wrong you indeed, then you ſhould conceiue and complaine that you are wronged. Laſtly, as for obligation and duty, mine towardes your Ladiſhippe is ſo greate, that this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration alone without any other motiue would haue beene ſufficient to make mee ſtraine my beſt indeavours to the higheſt, to ſtrike out ſome part of my ſcoare, if paper payment may bee currant, and verball ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement may ſatisfie for reall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefittes, which indeed cannot bee, but by the favourable acceptance of generous and noble mindes, who deeme that merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie beneficence is no beneficence. Of which temper knowing your Ladiſhips ſpirit
<pb facs="tcp:102:6"/>to be, I haue beene encouraged to ſhift out by this kinde of beggerly recompence. I heare therefore, deare Madame, preſent vnto you the Anatomie of my beſt thoughts, entreating your favorable acceptation thereof. To you are they due aboue al others, ſuch as they are being the fruits of that tree, to wit my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie ſelfe, that hath continually bin wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and cheriſhed by your manifold Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian favors. But here againe, I muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare particulars, leaſt I ſhould be offenſiue; and therefore I end, moſi affectionately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending your good Ladyſhip to the grace of God in Chriſt. <hi>Barſtable in Devonſhire 1609. Ianuarie 1. alias Newyeares day.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips moſt obliged RICHARD SMYTH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:102:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE CONTENTS</hi> of the ſeverall Chapters.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.</label> The vanity of all knowledge with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the right knowledg of our ſelues.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.</label> Agenerall conſideration of mans miſerie.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.</label> The Gentils miſerable ignorance of the true cauſe of mans miſerie.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.</label> That as the Gentils knew not the true cauſe of mans miſery, ſo neither did they know the vtmoſt and height of it.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.</label> That the Gentils being ignorant both of the cauſe and the greatnes of
<pb facs="tcp:102:7"/>mans miſery haue groſly erred in the true remedies againſt the ſame.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.</label> That true religion reveiled vnto vs by Gods word only diſcovereth vnto vs the cauſe of our miſerie.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.</label> The true remedies which Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religion affordeth againſt the firſt kinde of mans miſerie, that is, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils of paine.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 8.</label> That the Chriſtian religion onlie affordeth vs true remedie againſt the ſecond kinde of evils, that is, the evils which we do, or our ſinnes.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.</label> Conſolations againſt certaine cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of ſinne, namely long co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance therein before our conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and relapſe into it after our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:102:7"/>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 10.</label> Of the greatneſſe of Gods mercie, wherewith the greatnes of ſinne hath no proportion.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.</label> The Chriſtians peculiar comforts againſt death and the terror thereof.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 12.</label> Conſolations againſt the terrours of the generall iudgement.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.</label> The ioies of heaven, and glorious ſtate of the faithfull after death.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:102:8"/>
            <head>The ſinners counſell to his ſoule. <hi>A Sonnet of the Authors.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>A wake ô Soule, and looke abroad,</l>
               <l>Shake off this drowſie ſleepe of ſin,</l>
               <l>Shake off the clogs that thee ſo load,</l>
               <l>And to be wiſe at length begin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou commeſt of a race divine,</l>
               <l>Derived from the Deitie,</l>
               <l>And therefore ſhouldſt with vertue ſhine</l>
               <l>Such parentage to teſtifie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thou through Satans guile and ſpite</l>
               <l>Didſt ſhamefully degenerate,</l>
               <l>And now to ſenſe and appetite</l>
               <l>Thy ſelfe doſt baſely captivate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſo with vice art thou defilde,</l>
               <l>Which fowler is than leprouſie,</l>
               <l>That now thou ſeem'ſt no more Gods childe</l>
               <l>But one of Satans progenie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:102:8"/>
               <l>Appointed heyre of heavenly ioies</l>
               <l>With God himſelfe aboue to reigne,</l>
               <l>Thou doateſt here on earthly toyes,</l>
               <l>On ciphers, ſhaddowes meerely vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And here thou fooliſhly doſt thinke</l>
               <l>In pleaſures vaine, content to finde,</l>
               <l>While thou doſt but thy poiſon drinke,</l>
               <l>Such deadly dregs they leaue behinde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For pleaſure which in ſin men take</l>
               <l>Is in a moment gone and paſt,</l>
               <l>Whereas the wounds which it doth make</l>
               <l>Remaine behinde and ever laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And of ſuch wounds thou bearſt the print</l>
               <l>And with them fowly gaſhed art,</l>
               <l>Although that thou more hard than flint</l>
               <l>Felſt not at firſt their deadly ſmart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now that God in mercie great</l>
               <l>Good thoughts into thee daignes to ſend,</l>
               <l>And everlaſting death doth threat</l>
               <l>Except with ſpeede thou doſt amend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O flie thou from that monſter vile</l>
               <l>From ſubtill and inchanting ſinne.</l>
               <l>That hath ſo wrongd thee all this while</l>
               <l>And cauſe of ſuch annoyance bin.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:102:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:102:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:102:10"/>
               <l>The birds and beaſts that ſcape the ſnare</l>
               <l>Backe to the ſame no baite can traine,</l>
               <l>So wary afterwards they are,</l>
               <l>As never to come there againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then bluſh ô ſoule, that creatures mute</l>
               <l>The dangers paſt ſhould after ſhunne,</l>
               <l>And thou ſhouldſt be ſo mad and brute,</l>
               <l>As into them againe to runne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thinke how thou doſt thy ſelfe expoſe</l>
               <l>To danger deepe by every ſinne,</l>
               <l>Even heaven and heavenly ioies to loſe,</l>
               <l>And bell and belliſh woes to winne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For who ſo ventures to rebell</l>
               <l>Againſt the Lord and followes vice,</l>
               <l>His ſoule he to the divell doth ſell,</l>
               <l>And takes vaine pleaſure for her price.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then loath this world ſofull of ſnares</l>
               <l>A maze of errours. ſhop of lies,</l>
               <l>A ſtage of ſhaddowes, cage of cares,</l>
               <l>An Eccho of complaints and cries.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou ſeeſt all worldly ioyes deceiue:</l>
               <l>They promiſe to content the minde,</l>
               <l>And yet ſtill emptie doe it leaue,</l>
               <l>Which ſhewes they feed it but with winde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:102:10"/>
               <l>Then cleaue to God thine only ſtay</l>
               <l>Who for himſelfe did firſt thee make,</l>
               <l>From whom as long as thou doſt ſtray,</l>
               <l>In vaine thou ſeekeſt reſt to take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſhame not vnto him to flie,</l>
               <l>Nor let not terror hope confound:</l>
               <l>Although thy ſinnes for vengeance cry,</l>
               <l>Yet grace ſhall more than ſinne abound.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:102:11"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102:11"/>
            <head>MVNITION AGAINST MANS MISERY, AND <hi>Mortalitie.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> The vanity of all knowledge without the right knowledge of ourſelues.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>VRIOSITY, that is, exceſſiue care for thinges imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, and litle or no care for thinges important, is a vice ſo groſſe and ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the very Gentils by the light of nature in part perceived it, and ſo farre as they perceived it, reproved and condemned it.<note n="a" place="margin">Plut. de Curioſitate.</note> One of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath written a whole treatiſe of this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>encca ad Luc epiſt. 1.</note> An other complaines that a great part of our life ſlideth avvaie while we doe evill things, a greater while we do nothing, the greateſt of all while we doe things impertinent, and that concerne vs not. No mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile then if the ſonnes of light, that is, they that haue beene called to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102:12"/>ſaving knowledge of God in Chriſt, reveiled by the Goſpel haue ſo ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cenſured this vice, as<note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt. de Trin. l. 4. c, 1.</note> one of them doth in this maner, <hi>The knowledge of the world for the moſt part is accompanied with arrogancie, and curioſitie, whence it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe, that the world is ignor ant of things neceſſarie to be knowne, becauſe it learneth things needleſſe to be knowne.</hi> Alas what folly is it for men to take ſuch paines in the ſearch of thinges, that, as the<note n="d" place="margin">Sen. ep. 45</note> ſage Gentill ſaith, neither hurt him that is ignorant of them, nor profitte him that knowes them; &amp; in the mean ſeaſon neglect the things that tend to their true happines, &amp; can only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their ſound comfort &amp; content: at whome<note n="e" place="margin">Bernat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de Conſid. l. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> iuſtly ſcoffeth, <hi>Doubtleſſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>they very wiſely weigh and meaſure things, who haue: greateſt care for the ſmalleſt things, and ſmall or no care for the greateſt thinges.</hi> But the checke which<note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 10 v. 41.43.</note> our Lord Ieſus Chriſt himſelf giveth to this fault in reproving <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> that in ſome ſort was guilty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſhould moſt moue vs. <hi>Martha, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thou art troubled about many things, one thing is neceſſarie, Marie hath choſen the good part, which ſhall not be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102:12"/>2 And this vice &amp; vanitie is ſo much the greater, becauſe not only the knowledge of things meerely imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, and ſuperfluous, is vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble without the knowledge of thoſe things that belong to our true happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: but even the knowledge of things in part and in ſome degree ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary is ſo alſo.<note n="*" place="margin">Grammar.</note> What is the skill of Grammar worth, to know how to ſpeake by rule,<note place="margin">Rhetorick.</note> and in the meane ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to liue without rule? * What a vai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the art of Rhetoricke, that our language be eloquent,<note place="margin">Logiek.</note> and our man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners barbarous? * What good can Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke do vs, to be perfit in art of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, and yet that all our actions &amp; courſes are without reaſon yea flat re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pugnant to reaſon? to bee ſo armed therwith, that words ſhal not deceiue vs, and all the while to bee deceived with things themſelues; with cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes vnder pretence of thrift, and good husbandry; with prodigality vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of liberality, with crueltie vnder ſhew of ſeveritie, and ſo forth, which are the moſt pernicious errors of all,<note place="margin">Artithmetick</note> and farre exceede all ſophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call fallacies of words? * What bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit can Arithmeticke yeeld vs, to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102:13"/>to number all other things, &amp; to haue no care to number either our many ſinnes, or our few daies in this tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitory life?<note place="margin">Geometry.</note> * What can Geometrie availe vs, if we bee cunning in meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all other things, and yet to ſet no meaſure nor preſcribe any bounds to our infinite affections and paſſions, &amp; to keepe no meaſure either in our hopes or feares, proſperity or adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, ioies or ſorrowes?<note place="margin">Muſicke.</note> * What can Muſicke ſteed vs to diſcerne between concords and diſcords of ſounds, to be pleaſed with the former, and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the latter, and yet to haue our whole life conſiſt of nothing but diſcordes, iarring not only with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but alſo with our ſelues, having deſires contrary to deſires, reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s contrary to reſolutions? * What will knowledge in Phyſicke advantage vs:<note place="margin">Phyſicke.</note> if we haue learned what medicine or receipt is good againſt the gout, the dropſie, the ſtone, and other bodilie maladies; and yet haue no remedy for anger, envie, luſt, covetouſnes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſeaſes of the minde? To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, * What are we the better to be never ſo learned Lawyers,<note place="margin">Law.</note> and able to pleade never ſo ſufficiently either in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102:13"/>our owne or other mens cauſes for debts, houſes, lands and the like, &amp; to haue never a word to ſay for our ſelus whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we muſt plead for our own ſouls, how our infinite debt towards God in regard of our innumerable ſins may be diſcharged, and our title to a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly inheritance maintained &amp; iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Now if the knowledge of things in their place, and degree neceſſarie, be ſo vnavailable, and of ſo ſmal ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, without the knowledge of thoſe things which belong to our everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing happineſſe and welfare: much more is the knowledge of things ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, vnprofitable, and meerely vaine. It behoveth vs then to haue ſpeciall care to knowe thoſe thinges which ſo deepely concerne vs, and to make vſe of that excellent ſpeech<note n="*" place="margin">Aeſchylus.</note> of the very prophane Greek Poet, that <hi>he is wiſe, not who knowes many things, but who knowes profitable things:</hi> and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe true it is which a famon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian author wrote long agoe, that<note n="g" place="margin">Auguſt do trin. l. 4. c. 1.</note> that <hi>ſoule is more to bee commended which knowes her owne infirmity, then that which not knowing this labors to knowe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the world, the courſes of the ſtarres,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102:14"/>the bottome of the earth, the height of the heavens.</hi> Digreſſions in ſpeech and words are odious much more indeeds and action, and not only odious, but alſo dangerous and pernicious. And yet if wee duely examine our courſes, wee ſhall finde our whole life to bee nothing elſe but digreſſions, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies: and it is greatly to bee lamented that many thouſands even of thoſe that profeſſe chriſtianity, go out of the world before they conſider wherefore they came into it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> A generall conſideration of mans miſerie.</head>
               <p n="1">1. OF what importance the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our ſelues is, we haue heard in the former Chapter. Nowe this knowledge of our ſelues conſiſts in theſe two points: the knowledge of our miſery, and of the remedies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our miſery. Our miſery is two folde, or lieth in two kindes of evils, the evils which we doe, and the evils which we ſuffer, or as<note n="a" place="margin">Tertull, contra Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. l. 2. c. 14.</note> Divines long agoe haue diſtinguiſhed them, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>of fault, &amp; the evils of paine, that is, ſinne and the puniſhment of ſinne. Now although the laws of Method &amp; order require that I ſhould firſt ſpeak of the firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> namely the evils of faulte, as being the cauſe of the later, to weet the evils of paine: yet becauſe we are more moved with the puniſhments of ſinne, then with ſin it ſelfe, I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with that which is moſt ſenſible, applying my ſelfe herein to our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and groſneſſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The evils of paine are of tvvo ſorts. For the puniſhment of ſin is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther temporall, to weete all the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this preſent life; or eternall, that is to ſay, the tormentes of hell in the life to come. The former are ſo palpable, that the meere natural man feeles them, &amp; grones vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of them, as the complaints of the very heathen manifeſtly teſtifie.<note n="b" place="margin">Sen. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat, in natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                  <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> the miracle of nature for morall learning, cries out thus, <hi>Ah what a baſe and abiect creature is ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, except he adva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; lift vp himſelfe aboue ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that is, aboue the condition and ſtate of man,<note n="c" place="margin">Plin. natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. hiſt. l. 2, cap. 7.</note> An other ſaies that <hi>this only is certaine that nothing is certaine, and that there is not a more miſerable, nor yet for all that a more
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102:15"/>proude creature than man.</hi> And<note n="d" place="margin">Idem lib. 7 in prooem.</note> againe, that it is <hi>vncertaine, whether nature bee a kinder mother, or harder ſtep mother to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kind.</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Cic. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. lib. 3. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Auguſt. contra Iuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. lib. 4 c. 14, &amp; 15</note> A third renowned for his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and eloquence, complaines, that <hi>Nature hath brought man forth into the world, not as a mother but as a ſtep mother with a body, naked, weake, and ſickly, and a minde, diſtracted with cares, deiected with feares, faint for labour, and addicted to luſt, and pleaſures.</hi> And hence grew that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſpeech among the Gentils rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by<note n="f" place="margin">Ariſtot. in Eudemo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Plutare conſolat. ad Apolon.</note> 
                  <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> repeated<note n="g" place="margin">Cic. Tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c. quaeſt. lib. 1.</note> by <hi>Cicero,</hi> &amp;<note n="h" place="margin">Plut. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Plutarch,</hi> &amp; fathered by all three vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Silenus,</hi> that <hi>the beſt thing in the world was not to be borne, the next to die ſooneſt.</hi> And<note n="i" place="margin">Senec. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolat. ad Po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyb. e 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> againe exclaimes that <hi>our whole life is a penance.</hi> Which the <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> confirmed by their practiſe, cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s birth with wee ping and lamentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but their death with ioy &amp; mirth, as<note n="k" place="margin">Herodot. lib. 5. Solin. Poly. hiſt. cap. 15 Val Maxim. lib. 2 cap. 6.</note> divers ancient writers recorde, thereby inſinuating that our life was nothing but miſerie, and death the ende of miſerie. But<note n="l" place="margin">Bern de conſid. l. 2.</note> a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> author more effectually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth this point thus in ſubſtance, <hi>that if the greateſt man in the world do in a holy meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrip himſelfe out of his robes and ornaments of ſtate, which hee neither
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102:15"/>brought into the world with him at his birth, nor ſhall carrie out of the world with him at his death, he ſhall find himſelfe to be nothing but a man naked, poore, pitcous, and to be pitied, lamenting that he is a man, blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing that he is naked, weeping that hee is borne, and murmuring that he is at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 And thus much in generall (for particularitie would bee infinite) of mans miſery in regard of temporall paine, which is all that the heathen &amp; infidel apprehendeth For as for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny eternall puniſhment for ſinne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life, hee never dreames of it, nay makes a ieſt of it, as wee by Gods aſſiſtance ſhall ſee * hereafter.<note place="margin">Chap. 4, Sect. 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. But the Chriſtian proceedeth further, and touching evills of paine is moſt troubled with feare of eternal puniſhment for ſinne in the world to come. Hee hath learned out of Gods word<note n="m" place="margin">Exod. 20. v. 5.</note> that <hi>God is a iealous God and full of indignation</hi> when he is diſhonoured, and we knowe that <hi>ielouſie</hi> is the anger of angers,<note n="n" place="margin">Exod. 34. v. 7.</note> that <hi>the will in no wiſe abſolue the wicked and vngogly,</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Hab. 1. v. 13</note> that <hi>his eies are ſo pure, that they cannot endure to beholde iniquitie,</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 2, v. 6</note> that <hi>hee rewardeth every man accerding to his workes,</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Verſ 9.</note> that <hi>tribulation and anguiſh ſhall bee vpon every ſoule that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102:16"/>ſinneth,</hi> that <hi>the ſinner daily heapeth vp wrath againſt the day of wrath, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the righteous iudgement of God,</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">Heb. 10. verſ. 31.</note> that <hi>it is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the living God,</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Rom 5. verſ. 12.</note> that <hi>death came into the world by ſinne,</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 6. verſ. 21.</note> and <hi>is the end &amp; reward of ſinne,</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Heb. 9. verſ. 27.</note> that <hi>after death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth iudgement.</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">2. Cor. 5. verſ. 10.</note> and that <hi>we muſt all appeare before the iudgement ſeate of Chriſt to receiue our meed according to that which wee haue done in the fleſh, whether it bee good or evill,</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Matth. 8. verſ. 12. &amp; Marc. 9. v.</note> that <hi>whoſoever ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in this iudgement, ſhall bee caſt for ever into vtter darknes where there is wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Aug. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos aliquot ep. ad Rom. numero. 42.</note> Finally, the Chriſtian conſiders as Saint Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine ſaies, that <hi>every man by ſinning ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his ſoule to the devil, taking the ſvveet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of temporarie pleaſure for the price thereof.</hi> And thus much for the evils of paine that make mans ſtate ſo miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The ſeconde braunch of mans miſerie, are the evils of fault, or his ſinnes, which indeede is the greateſt part of his miſerie, although common<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly it be leaſt felt, and the Infidel ſcarſe feeles it at all. For as<note n="b" place="margin">Sen. ep. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8</note> a Heathen himſelfe well obſerved, <hi>Men are not greaved for their faults before they be gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102:16"/>with the bad ſucceſſe of their faults;</hi> that is, they are not ſorie for doing ill, but for ſpeeding ill, not that they are naught, but that they are wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, in a word, they greeue that they are miſerable, not that they are wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and worthie to be miſerable, that they are puniſhed, not that they haue deſerved to bee puniſhed. Which is verified not only in the common ſort of whome he meant it, but of the beſt amongſt the Gentils, yea of himſelfe too. For howſoever they ſeeme to teach ſometimes that vice is an evill of it ſelfe, as<note n="c" place="margin">Plato de Repub l 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Plato</hi> divinely affirmes that <hi>no man can doe wrong to another, but firſt hee muſt doe wrong to himſelfe,</hi> and<note n="d" place="margin">Plutarch. quod ſolum vitium ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat ad ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerum red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum.</note> another hath writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a whole Trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſe to proue, that <hi>vice</hi> alone is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to make a man miſerable which worke of his is pittifully mangled by iniurie of time yet they only appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend <hi>vice</hi> as a political or at the moſt a morall evill: a politicall evill for as much as it made men ſubiect to puniſhment, and obnoxious to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like iuſtice; or as a morall evill that ſtained and impaired their reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and credit in the world, &amp; hindered that delight which they tooke in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102:17"/>of their own imaginarie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, which was a meere ſhaddow or rather a deteſtable idoll.</p>
               <p n="6">6 But the Chriſtian, at leaſt the true Chriſtian is more moved vvith ſin than with the puniſhment of ſinne and apprehends ſin not only as a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall or morall evill, but as a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall evill, that is to ſay, as it defileth the ſoule and makes it odious vnto God, and defaceth his image in vs, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the which we were firſt made, tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming vs into the image &amp; likenes of Satan his and our ſworne enemie, in a word as it dayly worketh in vs in gratitude, diſobedience and rebellion againſt the moſt high, in whome wee liue, moue, and haue our being. Our ſinnes then are the evils of evils, and it is an vncontroulable principle in Divinity, that the leaſt evill of faulte is worſe then the greateſt evil of pain and that wee are bound rather to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the greateſt evill of paine, then to commit the leaſt evill of faulte. For as long as we bee meerely paſſiue and ſuffer only, although the things bee not only grievous, but alſo infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, they cannot hurt vs, nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger vs, but that rule will ever hold
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102:17"/>that no man is hurt but by himſelfe. Wherefore<note n="e" place="margin">Auguſt. de Civit. Dei lib <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cap. 19</note> S. Auguſtine ſaies of the raviſhing of <hi>Lucretia</hi> by <hi>Tarquinius,</hi> that <hi>Tarquiniꝰ &amp; Lucretia were two, &amp; yet it was but one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted adultery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7 Sinne then I ſay is that vvhich principallie makes a man miſerable, ſin is the very leproſie of the ſoule, ſinne tranſformes a man into a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and makes him a baſe degenerate creature, yea the worſt of all ſenſitiue creatures. This hath ſo altered man, that, as<note n="f" place="margin">Idem Ibid. lib 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> c. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> elegantly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it, <hi>he that ſhould haue beene ſpirituall in his fleſh, is now fleſhly in his ſpirite:</hi> his meaning is, that whereas if man had continued in his innocencie, his fleſh ſhould haue beene in a manner ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, becauſe all the ſenſes and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the fleſh ſhoulde haue beene comely, regular and holy, nowe his very ſpirit is become fleſhly, becauſe all the operations and motions of the very minde and ſoule are inordinate and vitious. And how fowly ſin hath deformed vs, and diſtempered nature, and what confuſion it hath vvrought in vs appeareth by this, that whereas the ſoule in man, whom ſome haue ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tearmed <hi>a little world,</hi> is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102:18"/>agent, &amp; the body the inſtrument, reaſon the Soveraigne, and appetite and ſenſe the ſubiects, ſin hath turned this little world quite vpſide downe. The body is become the maſter, and the ſoule the ſervant; or rather, the body a Lord, and the ſoule a ſlaue: ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite and ſenſe command and ſway, reaſon is brought into ſubiection vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and muſt do as they wil haue it. Thus as the common ſaying is, <hi>the cart drawes the horſe.</hi> The ſoule ſhould lift vp the body, but the body pulles downe the ſoule, and forceth her to ſuſpend her proper operations, that appetite and ſenſe may act all. Wee place cur happines not in things pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per to vs, as the right vſe of reaſon, contemplation of heavenly things, vnion with God, and the like, which indeed are the life of the ſoule, but in things common to vs, and beaſtes, in the ſatisfying, or rather glutting of appetite &amp; ſenſe, although<note n="g" place="margin">Sen. ep 93</note> the very Gentill could ſay, that <hi>pleaſure is the chiefe good of beaſtes.</hi> Nay ſinne makes vs worſe then beaſtes. For although beaſts are guided in all their actions with ſenſe and appetite only, yet are ſenſe and appetite in them ſo regular
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102:18"/>and vniforme, that they hold one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant courſe, only ſeeking to ſatisfie nature, not to oppreſſe it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neither ſurfe it with eating, nor are drunken with drinking, nor in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation betweene male and female exceede the neceſſitie of generation for multiplication and continuance of their like, which being accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, they afterwardes liue moſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately, and in all theſe things, as we vſe to ſay doe but their kinde. And all this they doe being deſtitute of reaſon and diſcourſe, herein more happy then man<note n="h" place="margin">Bernard. in Cantic. ſerm. 8.</note> as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> well ſaith, that <hi>they are not iudged, becauſe they themſelues cannot iudge.</hi> But man on whom God hath beſtowed reaſon to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duct, and direct him in his doings, diſdaineth to be governed by reaſon, yea purpoſely rebelleth againſt it, &amp; thinkes it his glory to bee vnreſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he deſpiſeth even pleaſure it ſelfe if it be naturall, and ſuch as God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth him, vſing artificiall enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as it were to diſguiſe Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and to forge newe delights of his own, although ſometimes they be rather torments then delights. Of all materiall and viſible creatures he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102:19"/>onely knowes order, and yet onelie breaks order, herein inferior not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to beaſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but to ſenſleſſe and life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe creatures. The ſea in ebbing &amp; flowing, the ſun and moone in riſing and ſetting, the ſtarres in moving and turning, the very earth in ſpringing and withering keepe a certaine order whereas man muſt needes be exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant and out of courſe, as if his reaſon had been given him to make him mad and void of reaſon.</p>
               <p n="8">8 And which not a little aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates this part of his miſerie, hee is ſo intangled in the ſnares of ſinne, that of himſelfe hee cannot poſſibly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvvine himſelfe, nay to ſpeake pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, hee truelie deſires not to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twine himſelfe, but whereas all other priſoners loath and hate their fetters the ſinner loues his, he is in bondage and yet is well pleaſed with his bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage. One would thinke that neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and vvillingneſſe vvere incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, and coulde not ſtande togither, yet ſinne hath ioined them in one, men cannot chuſe but ſinne, and yet are willing to ſin Thus,<note n="i" place="margin">Bernar in Cant. ſerm. 81.</note> as a divine author complaineth <hi>after a ſtrange ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, neither neceſſitie can excuſe the will, be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102:19"/>cauſe it is willing, nor yet the will ſhake of neceſſitie becauſe it is content to bee allured to evill, and to be over-ruled by ſuch neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity; So that this is after a ſort a willing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, a favorable or gentle violence, flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering vs while it forceth vs, and forcing vs while it flattereth vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9 And hence it is, that men often relapſe into the verie ſame ſinnes which they had formerly renounced and abiured The verie Gentiles per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and condemned this vanity or rather madneſſe of men ſo farre forth as it was a morall evill, the extent whereof we haue ſeene before,<note n="k" place="margin">See Barth Keckerman Syſtem. Eth. lib. 3. cap. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> was wont to ſay, that <hi>others thought a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be the wiſeſt creature that was, but for his part hee thought him to bee the moſt fooliſh, becauſe other creatures woulde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of thoſe things by whom they had bin once hurt, wheras ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oftentimes fals backe againe into the ſame vices:</hi> And<note n="l" place="margin">Sen. ep. 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; de vita beata ca. 28</note> as Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca expreſſes it, <hi>returneth to the thinges which he had given over, and condemned, forſaking what hee longed for, and againe longing for what he had forſaken, thus our loue and loathing of the very ſame thinges play their parts by turnes, and deſire and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe devide our life betweene them.</hi> And herein againe we muſt needs acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102:20"/>that ſinne makes vs worſe then beaſts. For ſaith<note n="m" place="margin">Hieron. ep. 10. ad. Furiam.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Ierom, the very ſeely beaſts and wandering birds will not bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken twice in the ſame traps or ſnares, &amp; yet fooliſh man relapſeth often into the ſame vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> that is indeed, is often taken in the very ſame ſnares of ſinne and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. This is the ſinners Labyrinth, or maze, whereinto being once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred he of himſelfe can never get out of it.</p>
               <p n="10">10 This I ſay is the evil of evils, &amp; makes man miſerable, even ſin conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in it ſelfe, without regarde of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny puniſhment either temporal or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, which notwithſtanding inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perably accompany the ſame. And ſurely the ſpiritual man cannot chuſe but be aſhamed of himſelfe, yea loath himſelfe, and conceiue indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelfe when he ſeriouſly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereth his ſinnes barely in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelus, both for the importa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reaſons before ſpecified, and alſo becauſe it is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable ingratitude againſt God, that he having made all other things for man, and man for himſelfe, thoſe other things do ſtill ſerue man, &amp; yet man will not ſerue God. O what vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindnes is this that God ſhould make
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102:20"/>all creatures ſerue vs, yea and a great many of them to maintaine our life by their death, and yet wee ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to ſerue him? This ſhould moſt pinch man; &amp; doth the ſpiritual man. And this is the proper difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene morall repentance, &amp; Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall repentance, that by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer men are grieved that they haue offended againſt honeſty, but, by the latter that they haue offended againſt piety. This made<note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 7, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.24.</note> the bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to cry out againſt the bondage of ſin in this paſſionate mann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. <hi>O wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man that I am, who ſhal d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body of death?</hi> He<note n="o" place="margin">2. Corinth 11. verſ 23.</note> elſe where makes mention of his impriſonments, his whippings, his ſtoning, and ſundry o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extremities, which hee had indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but none of theſe made him crie when he ſpake of them, only when he comes to ſpeake of his bondage vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the tyranny of ſinne, then he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but breake out into wofull exclamation. And the ſame affection although not the ſame degree of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is in all the godly, that abhorre ſinne even as hell it ſelfe<note n="p" place="margin">Aug epiſt, 144.</note> as S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> notably ſaith. <hi>Hee that is afraid of hell fire, is not afraid to ſin but to burne; he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102:21"/>is afraid to ſin, that hateth ſin it ſelf as he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth hell fire.</hi> And thus haue I in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall decyphred and diſcovered mans miſerie, I ſay only in general, for to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomize it in particular, were to roaue in a ſea that hath neither bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome nor ſhoare. It remaineth that we ſhould nowe come to the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies thereof but that I thinke it ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pedient firſt to ſpeake of the cauſe thereof, ſith the knowledge of the cauſe of any evil brings great light to the cure; and before that againe to ſhewe mans groſſe ignoraunce of the right cauſes of his miſery, and this God willing ſhall be the argument of the next Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> The gentils miſerable ignoraunce of the true cauſe of mans miſerie.</head>
               <p n="1">1 VVe haue heard in the former chapter, that mans miſery is ſo ſenſible, that the very heathens haue apprehended it, and much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained thereof, ſpecially of the evils that man ſuffers in this world: for as for the evils which he doth, which are far the greater, &amp; of greater force to make him miſerable, they were but coldly touched therewith. But as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102:21"/>the cauſe, either of the one, or the other kinde of miſerie, they were altogither ignorant thereof, &amp; therfore no marvel if they knewe not the true remedies either againſt the one or the other. And ſurely touching the cauſe of mans miſery their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts &amp; coniectures were ſo ſtrange, that it is doubtful whether we ſhould more piety them, or laugh at them.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The general co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceipt of the moſt ſufficient among them, much more of the vulgar ſort was that the firſt bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch of mans miſery, namely the manifold and grievous evils which he ſuffereth in this life, grew from this, that Gods providence was confined in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er parts of the worlde, and deſcended not nor extended to things below the moone. Of this opinion were manie Philoſophers. <hi>Many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">Auguſt. de Geneſi ad literam.</note> S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, <hi>haue thought, that indeede the high partes of the worlde are governed by Gods providence, but that this lowe parte of the earth and the aire next aboue it, vvhere windes and clowds do riſe, are rather toſſed to &amp; fro by caſuall motions.</hi> In this error was <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelfe, who thought that Gods care for the affaires of the world, reached not below the moone,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102:22"/>as a great many of the chiefeſt anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fathers report of him, but aboue the reſt<note n="b" place="margin">Ambrol. de offic. lib. 1. ca. 13.</note> S. <hi>Ambraſe,</hi> who moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently confures that his profane fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie at large, and I cannot here omit one golden ſpeech of his that way,<note n="*" place="margin">Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ator negli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gat operis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ui curam? Quis deſerat aut deſtitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> at quod iple condendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> putatits Si iniutia eſt regere, non ne eſt maior iniuria fecil ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid non fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſſe nulla ſit iniuſtitia non curare antem quod feceris ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clementia.</note> 
                  <hi>What workeman,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>can neglect the care of his worke? who can forſake and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon that which himſelfe thought meete to make? if it be a wrong to God to rule, was it not a greater wrong in him to make? Sith not to haue made a thing at al is no iniuſtice, but not to care for that which one hath made, is greater crueltie.</hi> Thus the moſt iudicious Philoſopher dreamed that God had no care of men nor their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and therefore no marvaile if he in<note n="c" place="margin">Plaut cap. in prologo.</note> the Poet, ſpeaking popularly cry out,<note n="*" place="margin">Enim vero Dii no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> qua fipilas ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent.</note> that <hi>the Gods made tennisbals of men, toſſing them to and fro they cared not how</hi> Hence then, namely from Gods neglect and contempt of men &amp; their affaires, ſome held that mans ſo miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſtate in this world did proceed.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Others thinking this too groſſe, &amp; that ſuch an imputation did much derogate from the wiſedome &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of god, deviſed another ſhift and ſtarting hoale to helpe the matter, to weete that mens ſoules were created
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102:22"/>long before their bodies, and lived in heaven, but committing ſome great offence there, were condemned to be ioined vnto bodies here on earth, and ſo to endure thoſe infinite miſeries wherevnto mans life is ſubiect, by way of pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for the faults they had done in heaven. And this being firſt forged by heathens, ſeemed ſo proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and was ſo plauſible, that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards many great perſons in the very Church alſo greatly liked it, and ſet it abroach. Touching the Gentils<note n="d" place="margin">Cicero in Hortenſio apud Aug. contra Iuli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> an. l. 4. c. 12. &amp; 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> himſelfe profeſſed his approbation of this opinion, namely that we were borne into this wretched worlde for ſome fowle matters co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted before in a former world to ſuffer puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t here for the ſame. Who alſo compares mans caſe herein to that of thoſe, which fel into the hands of theeues of Tuſcany me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who were dealt with after this lamentable manner The one halfe of them were left aliue the other halfe murthered, then the living were bound backe to backe to the dead, and ſo rotted with them; and that even ſo our ſoules were coupled with our bodies, as the living with the dead for the greater
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102:23"/>torment And as for Divines in the Church, that they alſo applauded to this invention and vaine imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, appeareth by the teſtimonie of S.<note n="e" place="margin">Hieronim. epiſt. 8 ad Demetriad.</note> 
                  <hi>Ierem,</hi> who warneth a religious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his time to take heed of the Origeniſts who vſed to buzze into the eares of the ſimpler, that very rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained them to beleeue, that mens ſoules had lived in heaven firſt, and that for ſome old faults commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there, they were puniſhed here, &amp; adiudged to be put into bodies as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to priſons, and to doe penance in this vale of teares. And the reaſon that conſtrained them to bee of this minde, was forſooth, that yong chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren many times were borne defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and monſtrous, were ſubiect to ſickneſſe, and greevous pangs, &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times were puniſhed with death it ſelfe before they had actually offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which could notſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with Gods iuſtice, vnleſſe they had ſinned before their comming into the world. The vanitie of which imagination ſhall, God willing appeare hereafter. Thus they ſeeling this part of mans miſery and not knowing the cauſe thereof, runne into many ſottiſh errors<note n="f" place="margin">Auguſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bi ſupta hac ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ct. lit. mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. d.</note> as S.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102:23"/>
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith of <hi>Tullie, Hee ſawe the thing but knew not the cauſe of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 And as for the cauſe of the other and greater evill, namely ſinne, the generall opinion and conceit was, that it proceeded only, either from il education, or at the leaſt from mans bad husbanding of his owne free will which was equally inclinable to good or evill. Which if they had vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the firſt man Adara when he fell, had beene true and ſound: but of this they never dreamed. They thought that man conſidered in the ſtate of corrupt nature, or as hee is now of himſelfe, was without ſinne by birth, and had equall power to do good or evill, to be vertuous or viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and as I ſaid, that it was only bad education and imitation of the bad, or bad imploiment of his freewill &amp; naturall faculties of his ſoule, that made him naught; in which errour wee finde the very beſt and wiſeſt to haue been<note n="g" place="margin">Cie, Aead. quae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>woud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: &amp; Tuſculan lib. 4.</note> The Stoicks, the beſt of all Philoſophers for moralitie, were ſo blinded herein, that they thought even good and lawfull affections to be meerely of ill cuſtome, not of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, much more that corrupt and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102:24"/>affections were ſo. And<note n="h" place="margin">Seneca epiſt 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> brings in nature complaining of her children as degenerate, and telling them that ſhe brought the forth with out paſſions, and evill deſires &amp; luſts, without feares, without ſuperſtition, without trechery, &amp; the like; &amp;<note n="i" place="margin">Seneca c. piſt. 116.</note> in an other place makes this the only cauſe that we are naught, becauſe wee vvill not vſe the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth which nature hath give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs to ſhake of our vices, which is abundantly ſufficient to doe it. <hi>Not to bee willing ſaith hee, is the cauſe hereof: but not to be able is made the pretence and colour.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap 5. Sect. 8.</note> We ſhal haue occaſion * here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to ſpeake more of this blindnes and madneſſe of the Gentils touching the cauſe of this part of mans miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, namely ſinne, when wee ſhal come to handle the remedies which they preſcribed for the ſame. And as for the falſhoode thereof it ſhall bee ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed * in place convenient.<note place="margin">Chap. 6. Sect 4.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> That as the Gentiles knewe not the true cauſe of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s miſery ſo nether did they know the vtmoſt height of it.</head>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:102:24"/>
               <p n="1">1 AS wee haue ſeene in the former Chapter that the blinde hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s knew not the cauſe of mans mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, ſo it reſteth to bee here declared that they knew not the true meaſure and greatnes thereof, nay were meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignorant of many principall bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2 One ſpeciall point of our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is, that by ſinne we incurre the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of God, and become liable to his wrath and vengeance, who by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is an adverſary to all ſinne and ſinners,<note place="margin">Chap. 3. ſect. 1.</note> as hath beene * before ſhewed at large But this the heathens appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended not. For not only<note n="a" place="margin">Ovid. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor lib 3. eleg. 3. &amp; de arte aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di. lib. 1.</note> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane Poet imagined, that God did wincke at mens ſins, yea allow them, nay laugh at them, but alſo the chiefe Philoſophers thought &amp; taught that God was not offended with any thing that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did, much leſſe would puniſh it.<note n="b" place="margin">Sen. ep. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> the moſt morall of them, and the wonder of wit tels vs, <hi>that no man knowes God, and that many thinke ill of him, and that without any danger.</hi> In<note n="c" place="margin">Idem de bene fici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s lib. 7. c. 1.</note> another place hee thinkes hee hath ſpoken wiſely, when he ſpeakes moſt beaſtly, ſaying that one principall point for the attainement of perfect
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102:25"/>happineſſe is, to ſhake of all feare of God and man, and to reſolue that we are not to feare much from man, but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God nothing at all.<note n="d" place="margin">Idem de ira l. 2. c. 27.</note> In another, that <hi>there are ſome that haue neither will nor power to hurt, as the Gods, whoſe nature is wholy mild and gentle, and who are of power only to relieue and cheriſh, but not to annoy or affl ct.</hi> And<note n="e" place="margin">Plutarch. tractat de ſuperſtit.</note> another famous both for his learning and diligence, yea for his vertue too, ſo far as heath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh blindnes would permit, makes it flat ſuperſtition, to thinke that God would hurt any, being ſuperlatiuely good, yea goodnes it ſelfe: both being childiſhly deceived in this, that they thought, that for God to puniſh anie for their wickednes, and to do harme were all one,<note n="*" place="margin">See Tertul cent. Marci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> on. lib. 2. c. 14. &amp; Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant. de ira Dei cap. 17.</note> whereas it is a maine branch of his goodnes to hate evil, &amp; take vengeance on evill doers. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which no earthly Prince de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues the name, nor can maintaine the reputation of good.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Secondly they bewraye moſt groſſe ignorance touching mans mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery in this, that they thinke it is all ended by death: whereas the far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more grievous part thereof followeth after death, as we haue hard
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102:25"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 2. ſect. 4.</note> before. Yet herein the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned of them haue ſhamefully er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, &amp; drawne others into error.<note n="f" place="margin">Cie Tuſe. quaeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ib 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> in a large diſcourſe takes it for gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that after death men either ſhall be happy, or elſe not be at all.<note n="g" place="margin">Senec de remediis fortui. orum</note> 
                  <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> peremptorily avoucheth, that <hi>all things are ended by death, yea death it ſelfe.</hi> Which ſpeech of his<note n="h" place="margin">Tertul. de reſurrect. carnis cap. 2. &amp; de ani. ma cap. 42.</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> both iuſtly reproues, and pithily confutes. And in<note n="i" place="margin">Sen. conſo ſat, ad Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triam. c. 19</note> another place the ſame <hi>Sene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> more diſtinctly affirmeth, that <hi>thoſe things that make bell ſo terrible vnto vs, are but a meer fable, that no darknes, no priſon, no lake of fire are appointed for any after death, that there ſhall be none arraig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, no iudge to condemne, that thoſe that deviſed theſe things haue but frighted vs with ſcarre-crowes, that death is the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and end of all griefes, beyond which our evils do not reach.</hi> The ſame in effect is delivered by<note n="k" place="margin">Epict. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertat. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cap. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Epictetus,</hi> otherwiſe almoſt more then an humane author. But moſt blindly and profanely of all others writes<note n="l" place="margin">Plin. hiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at. lib 7. cap 55.</note> 
                  <hi>Pliny</hi> hereof, although in moſt elegant words and plauſible language. The ſumme whereof is this that <hi>all men are in the ſame caſe after their laſt day, as they were before the firſt day, and that there is no more feeling either in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102:26"/>the body or ſoule after the day of their death than there was before the day of their birth, that they may thinke otherwiſe are fooliſh and abſurde, as if there were any difference betweene the manner of mans breathing, &amp; other creatures, or as if there were not many other creatures of longer continuance than man, of whoſe eternitie notwithſtanding no man dreames, that theſe are but childiſh i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations, and falſe conceipts of mortality that affects immortality. and woulde never haue an end, &amp;c.</hi> Thus were the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens ignorant of the chiefeſt braun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of mans paſſiue miſery, namelie Gods vengeance on ſinners, and the full execution thereof after death in the world to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> That the Gentils being ignorant both of the cauſe and the greatneſſe of mans miſery, haue groſſely erred in the true remedies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame.</head>
               <p n="1">1 NOw the blinde heathens being ſo groſſely ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t both of the cauſe, &amp; alſo of the meaſure &amp; great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mans miſery, it muſt needs be that they were ignorant of the true
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102:26"/>remedies for the ſame. The things that make mans ſtate ſo miſerable, as hath * formerly beene ſaid, are prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally two, the evils wee ſuffer,<note place="margin">Chap. 2. ſect. 1,</note> and the evils which we do, vvith the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer whereof carnal &amp; natural me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are moſt moved, although they ſhoulde be moſt moved with the latter,<note place="margin">Chap. 2, ſect. 6.</note> * as hath bin ſhewed. Touching the evils which we ſuffer, as ſickneſſe, famine, peſtilence, war, poverty, baniſhment, impriſonment, torments at our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies pleaſure, vnhappy matches, and the like both innumerable and into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable croſſes, and laſt of all death it ſelfe, which although to natural men it hath ſeemed the end of all evils, yet withal they haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it for the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt evill, the remedies which they by their beſt meditation and ſtudy could deviſe againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are very poore, yea miſerable, and therefore vnfit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue miſery.</p>
               <p n="2">2 For let vs heare what they can ſay touching theſe thinges that ſo much trouble &amp; vex vs in this world. Indeed me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ſtrained their ſpirits to the higheſt, &amp; wonderouſly labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to fortifie their mindes againſt all occurrents of that nature, but vvith
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102:27"/>poore and pitifull ſucceſſe For if we reade thoſe which with moſt particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity haue handled this argument, as two ſpecially haue done<note n="a" place="margin">Senec. de remediis fortuit.</note> the one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,<note n="b" place="margin">Petrarch. de remed. vtriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunae.</note> the other of later times, wee ſhall ſee they feed vs with words and winde, and giue vs only verball com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts againſt reall evills. I muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare the particulars, and inſiſt only in thoſe generall remedies wherein all agree. The firſt was deviſed by the founder of the Stoicall profeſſion Zeno, and carries a goodly ſhewe of ſecuring vs that way.<note n="c" place="margin">Cic Tuſe. quaeſt. lib. 2.</note> His beſt mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition againſt this branch of humane miſery was that nothing could make a man miſerable but evill, that onely vice is evill, and therefore that onely vice could make a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſerable; that poverty, ſickneſſe, baniſhment, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, cold, hunger, famine, whipping, racking, cruell kindes of death, were no vices, and therefore no evills; no evills, and therefore could not make vs miſerable. And<note n="d" place="margin">Sence. de conſtant. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pient. ſive de tranquil. vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. lib. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> ſtraines the point yet farther telling vs, that a wiſe and vertuous man cannot be wronged by any. But alas, what poore and cold comforts are theſe? What, is ſickneſſe, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:102:27"/>famine, whipping, racking, hanging, burning, and other like, or greater torments the leſſe or eaſier, becauſe I am told they are no evils? What fond cavillation and ſophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call deluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is this, that becauſe theſe be not evils of fault, therefore they be not evils of paine, or no evills at all.<note n="e" place="margin">Cicer. qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſupra hac ſect. lit. mar. giu c.</note> A heathen author himſelfe iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laughs at this vanitie, and pithily confutes it <hi>The Stoics,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>conclude by certaine v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ine cavillations, that pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, or griefe is no evill, as though the word [evil] did trouble vs not the thing. Why doſt thou mocke me ô Zeno? for when thou denieſt that which is ſo terrible to me to be an evill, thou doſt but couſen me, and I would glodly know of thee, why that which ſeemes to mee moſt miſerable, ſhould not bee evill. Thou ſaiſt that nothing is evil, but that which is naught and diſhoneſt. In ſo ſaying thou doſt but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to thy olde fooleries: for by all this thou doſt not take away the things that tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment me. I knowe well enough that paine is not wickedneſſe. Never tell me what I know well enough already, proue to me that there is no oddes in the matter, whether I bee in paine or not in paine.</hi> And here it is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of obſervation, that when theſe Gallants that thus in wordes braved
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102:28"/>al outward paine and griefe incident to the body, came to practice &amp; acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they recanted theſe brags, which they had vttered in their idle ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. So <hi>Tullie</hi> himſelfe who much inclined to this paradox of the <hi>Stoics,</hi> and laboured to fortifie his ſpirit thereby againſt theſe evils of paine, when it came to triall, miſerably diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered his weakneſſe, &amp; that in the leaſt and lighteſt of theſe externall croſſes, namely baniſhment<note n="f" place="margin">Dio Caſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us hiſt Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. lib. 38.</note> For hee ſo baſely behaved himſelfe therein, that one <hi>Philiſcus</hi> of his olde acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance ſharply reproved him for the ſame: and ſpecially becauſe himſelfe had ſpoken and written ſo ſtoutly in contempt of all ſuch caſuall grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; given very good counſell to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Whoſe poore excuſe of ſuch his weakeneſſe was, that it was one thing to adviſe others, and another to comfort our ſelues when the caſe was our owne. But moſt memorable to this purpoſe is the behaviour of<note n="g" place="margin">Cie. Tuſe. quaeſt. lib 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Heracleotes Dionyſius Zenoes</hi> own ſchol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler, by whome having beene taught this ſtout contempt of paine, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no evill, afterwards having a bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and extreame fit of the ſtone, hee
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102:28"/>recanted his error, and cried out that all which his maſter had maintained touching that point was falſe, &amp; that hee now found and felt the contrary, namely that paine was an evill.</p>
               <p n="3">3 A ſecond ſuppoſed remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe evils of pain both taught and practiſed by carnall men is volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary death, or ſelfe murther, whereby men at their pleaſure might free the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from all theſe evills of paine. Herevpon<note n="h" place="margin">Oedipus apud Sence The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ai act 1. Sen. 1.</note> he cries out in the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy, that <hi>death is to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d every where, and that God in this hath provided won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous well for mankinde:</hi> that, <hi>whereas any man may take our life from vs, none can take death from vs,</hi> meaning that none can let vs from dying, having power to kill our ſelues when we pleaſe. And leaſt we ſhould thinke this to bee but a Poeticall fiction whereby men are made to ſpeake what the Poet plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, let vs heare the wiſeſt and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt of the Gentiles ſpeaking in good earneſt of this matter.<note n="i" place="margin">Quintil. inſtit. or at. li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emio.</note> 
                  <hi>Quinti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> affirmes that <hi>no man is long in paine, or ſorrow, vnleſſe it bee through his owne fault,</hi> meaning that by killing himſelf he may be rid of it when he pleaſeth. Yea even <hi>Seneca</hi> himſelfe appr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ues
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102:29"/>of this ſelfe-murther or killing our ſelues to ende all paine. Are we in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe and miſerie? <hi>Why,</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Sen ep. 12</note> ſaith hee, <hi>there are many and ſhort and eaſie waies to free our ſelues. Let vs giue thankes to God, that no man can be compelled to liue whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he will or no.</hi> And<note n="i" place="margin">Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ep. 70.</note> againe, <hi>If thou wilt follow my counſell, ſo prepare thy ſelfe, that thou maiſt entertaine death, nay if need be, that thou maiſt ſend for it. For it makes no matter whether death come to vs, or wee goe to death.</hi> Yea<note n="m" place="margin">Sen. ep. 71</note> hee mockes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rides thoſe that made any ſcruple thereof. And<note n="n" place="margin">Idem de ira lib. 3. c. 15</note> in another place, ſaith he, <hi>Which way ſoever thou lookeſt, there is an ende of all evils to bee found. Doſt thou ſee an high and ſteepe place, by falling down from it, thou ſhalt fall into liberty; feeſt thou ſuch a ſea, ſuch a river, or ſuch a pitte, liberty lies in the bottome of them, if thou haue the loart to caſt thy ſelfe into them. Doſt thou ſee a tree whereon others haue beene hanged, there hangs liberty, if thou wilt hang thy ſelfe. Doſt thou ſee thy owne necke, throate, heart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c, they are all places of eſcape to flie away from bondage. Are theſe too hard and painfull meanes to get out, and wouldſt thou yet knowe the way to liberty? Every vaine in thy body is a way to it.</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Sen. ep, 89.</note> Againe he tels vs, that if ſickneſſe bee incurable, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:102:29"/>diſable the ſoule to execute her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per actions, ſhee may as well goe out of ſuch a body at her pleaſure, as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may out of a rotten and ruinous te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement, or dwelling houſe. So<note n="p" place="margin">Epict. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertat lib. 2. cap. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pictetus</hi> himſelfe the wonder of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane both wiſdome and piety, ſaies that as they are fooles, who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue ſufficiently refreſhed themſelus at a feaſt, yet will ſit longer, yea even vntill they loath their meate, and are ready to vomitte, ſo they are fooles, that having had their fill of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life, yet will liue longer. And in<note n="q" place="margin">Epict. lib. 1 diſſert. c. 24</note> another place, <hi>Even as,</hi> quoth hee, <hi>boyes when they are wearie of any player ſport vſe to ſay, I will play no longer: ſo men when they are weary of living, muſt ſay, I will liue no longer.</hi> And therefore in<note n="r" place="margin">Idem lib. 1. cap. ſen. diſſertat. 9.</note> an other place hee laughes at their ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity that complaine of poverty &amp; want, <hi>What fooles,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>are they that when they haue filled their bellies to day, ſit weeping and penſiue bethinking what they ſhall eate to morrow. Baſe ſlaue, if thou haue meate, thou haſt it: if thou haſt it not, thou maiſt be packing out of the world, the dore is open.</hi> So<note n="ſ" place="margin">Sen. ep. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> highly commends that ſpeech of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> that <hi>indeed it was a miſery to liue in neceſſitie, but that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102:30"/>there was no neceſſity for a man to liue in neceſſitie.</hi> Meaning that every man by killing himſelfe might free himſelfe from it. Yea which is ſtrange<note n="t" place="margin">Plato de legibus l. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Plato</hi> himſelfe, that approached ſo neere to Chriſtian truth in many points, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he appoint ſome publike in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy in the maner of burial for thoſe that kill themſelues, yet it is with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers exceptions, and amongſt others this is one, <hi>if a man ſo doe by meanes of povertie and want.</hi> And to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude<note n="u" place="margin">Plin. nat. hiſt. lib. 2. cap. 63.</note> 
                  <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> would haue vs beleeue, that <hi>our mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther the earth having pitty vpon vs, doth bring forth poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> that we may diſpatch our ſelues out of this wretched world when there ſhall be due occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And this was practiſed by thoſe that were counted very worthy men,<note n="x" place="margin">Plutarch. in vita Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. Do Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſt Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, lib. 43.</note> as by <hi>Cato</hi> when <hi>Pompey</hi> whoſe part hee had taken was overthrowne by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling himſelfe, as it was conceived, principally becauſe he would not be beholding to <hi>Caeſar</hi> for his life, or at leaſt would not be put to death at his pleaſure.<note n="y" place="margin">Cornel. Nepo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta Tit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon. Attici.</note> Likewiſe by <hi>Pomponius At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus,</hi> who being impatient of a cruell diſeale that tooke him in his olde age, willingly famiſhed himſelfe to death, and could not bee diſſuaded
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:102:30"/>from ſo doing by the prayers and teares of his neareſt and deareſt allies and friends. But particulars of this nature are infinite, and therefore let theſe ſuffiſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Now howe poore a remedie this is for a man to kill himſelfe when he is in miſery, may ſufficiently appeare by that which hath already beene ſpoken touching the wofull ſtate of man after this life dying out of Gods favour, as they that thus make away themſelues needs muſt. So that this is not to avoid miſery, but to change miſery, yea to change the leſſer miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries for the greater, and as wee vſe to ſpeak, to leap out of the frying pan into the fire. Yea the Gentils them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſaw at laſt the vanitie &amp; abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of this remedy, deriding thoſe that becauſe they would not be put to death by others, put themſelues to death.<note n="z" place="margin">Sen. ep. 71</note> 
                  <hi>Seneca,</hi> who as wee haue ſeene ſo much favoured this prophane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, yet in ſome places forgetting himſelfe, truely ſaies, that <hi>it is follie for a man to die for feare of death:</hi> and<note n="a" place="margin">Martial e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigt. lib 22. epigram. 80</note> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaies it is madneſſe,<note n="*" place="margin">Hic rogo no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uror eſt ne moriare mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>I pray thee,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is not this madnes to dy leaſt thou ſhouldſt die?</hi> Others haue ſeene the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulnes
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102:31"/>hereof, namely<note n="b" place="margin">Cicero de ſenect. &amp; in ſomnio Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pionis.</note> that this is <hi>to forſake the ſtanding wherein God our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall hath placed vs, and to refuſe &amp; ſhun the office which God hath aſſigned vs in this world:</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Ariſt. Eth lib 3. cap. 7.</note> others, obſerue the baſeneſſe of it, <hi>that it is a token of a coward, and not of a valiant man, ſith valure conſiſts in a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient enduring of al extremities.</hi> And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note n="d" place="margin">Martial. epigram.</note> the very profane Poet ſcoffes at <hi>Cato</hi> for killing himſelfe, of whom we haue heard before, truely affirming, that <hi>it is an eaſie matter to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne death in our miſery, &amp; that he is the valiant ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patietly beare miſerie.</hi> Yea<note n="e" place="margin">Virgil, Aed. lib. 6.</note> ſome haue gone farther, and ſeene the danger hereof alſo, namely that it is puniſhed in the life to come, placing thoſe that haue offended that way in hell, &amp; that in ſuch torments, as they wiſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues backe againe, &amp; vpon that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition would be content to endure al the miſeries incident to this life. Lo the poore remedies that nature can teach vs againſt this firſt kinde of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, namely the evils which we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Now touching the evils which wee do, which as hath beene ſhewed, we ſhould hold the greateſt, as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall men haue leſſe knowne and felt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:102:31"/>them than the former, ſo haue they beene leſſe either carefull or able to finde out any ſound and effectuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies againſt them, nay I may bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeake it, that as they giue vs foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Phyſicke againſt the former, ſo they giue vs ranck poiſon againſt the later. And as it fals out in bodily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Phyſitian miſtake the cauſes of them, they apply medicines cleane contrary, and ſuch as exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the evill not aſſwage it; ſo it fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with the maladies of the minde, if they that profeſſe skil to cure them erre in the originall ground of them, inſteed of healing them they poyſon them and make them far worſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The guilt of ſinne which al men carry in their boſome tels them that ſinne needes ſome purgation and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piation, or elſe they muſt incurre the indignation and vengeance of God. But when it comes to particulars, what the true meanes of delivering vs from the danger of ſinne ſhould be, here the wit of man is a ground and vtterly amazed and confounded, and the beſt remedies it can deviſe in this caſe are either fooliſh as wee haue ſeene they were againſt the firſt kind
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102:32"/>of evils, namely of paire, or els impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and wicked.</p>
               <p n="7">7<note n="f" place="margin">See Natal. Comes My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiol. l. 1. c. 11.12.</note> Some thought that ſinne was blotted out &amp; Gods wrath appeaſed by offering of flowers, franckincenſe, and other ſweere perfumes, but ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that every meane perſon coulde be as liberal that way as <hi>Alexander</hi> the great,<note n="g" place="margin">Plutarch. Apopht Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum. &amp; Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat.</note> who vſed to ſacrifice with ſo much franckincenſe at a time, that <hi>Leonidas</hi> his ſteward reproved him for it, telling him that hee muſt firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer the country where frankincenſe grew, before he waſted it ſo prodigal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuppoſe, I ſay, every man could be ſo coſtly in that reſpect. yet who that is well adviſed, can dreame, that the ſweet ſmell of hearbs &amp; perfumes can take away the filthy ſtinke of ſinne? Others thought by certain waſhigns with peculiar &amp; hallowed waters the filth of ſinn was waſht away, as if that which made the skin cleane, made the heart alſo cleane, and that purifie the minde which never came neere the minde. Others truely iudging theſe cures to bee light, and ſuperficial, though it muſt be death and bloud at leaſt that muſt do away ſinne, vſually killed beaſts of al ſorts in great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102:32"/>and ſacrificed them to appeaſe Gods anger, and make ſatisfaction for their tranſgreſſions. But heare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine reaſon awaked will tell vs, that if all men còuld bee as bountifull as <hi>Iulian</hi> the Roman Emperour vſually was,<note n="h" place="margin">Ammian. Marcellin. lib. 25.</note> of whom the ieſt went, that if he had returned with victorie in his laſt actions againſt the <hi>Parthians,</hi> the very kinde and race of buls, oxen, and kyne would haue beene extinguiſhed by meanes of his monſtrous exceſſe in ſacrificing of beaſts, if, I ſay, everie man could and ſhould be at ſuch coſt that way: yet what ſtrange blindneſſe were it to thinke that the bloud of beaſts could purge the ſinnes of men, or that man ſhould commit the fault, and beaſtes ſhould beare the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it?</p>
               <p n="8">8 But the remedies which the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural man deviſed againſt this ſecond branch of our miſery namely ſinne, were not only fooliſh, but alſo wicked &amp; pernicious For firſt, ſome looking further into the matter, and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that it was no reaſon, that man ſhould offende and beaſtes ſhould be puniſhed, &amp; die for his offences, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that in all equitie man muſt be
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102:33"/>puniſhed for the faults of man.<note n="i" place="margin">See Natal. Comes My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol. l. 1. c. 8.</note> And therefore moſt nations vſed to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice certaine men at certaine times of the yeare to make an atonement for the ſinnes of all the reſt. So<note n="k" place="margin">Plutarch tractat. de ſupe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginians</hi> ſacrificed their own childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to <hi>Saturne,</hi> being preſent thereat, and looking on, and ſuch as had no chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of their owne, bought the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the poorer ſort, as if they had beene lambs, or goates, and the order was, that the very mothers of them muſt be preſent at the ſacrifice with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making any ſhewe of ſorrowe or compaſſion at the ſight, and if they did, they forfeited the price of them, and yet their children were ſacrificed nevertheleſſe. The wickednes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is ſo palpable, that<note n="l" place="margin">Silius Ita li cus lib. 4. Lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cret. lib. 2.</note> ſome of the heatheniſh idolatours the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, and cried out againſt it, yea<note n="m" place="margin">Plutarch. quo ſupra.</note> ſome were ſo moved therwith, that they diſputed the point whether A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme were not far better, then ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, and much inclined to the affirmatiue part.<note n="n" place="margin">Lucret. quo ſupra.</note> Others here vpon directly became Atheiſts, crying out that religion was the cauſe of all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety. And which is yet more ſtrange, the Gentils were ſo blinde in this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102:33"/>point, that ſome of them,<note n="o" place="margin">Strab. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> as the <hi>Leu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cades,</hi> yearly made choice of ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious malefactour, &amp; ſacrifized him for the vvhole, as though his death could expiate the ſins of others, who had deſerved many deathes for his owne ſinnes: vvhereas indeede<note n="p" place="margin">Bernard. ad Milites templi, c. 4.</note> the death of the beſt man now in the ſtate of ſinne cannot profit an other, ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h every man oweth a death for himſelf. But as hath beene ſaid, this remedy is not only fooliſh &amp; vnprofitable, but alſo impious and deteſtable,<note n="q" place="margin">Ang. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit. Deili. 6. cap. 12.</note> making God more cruell than any man; for what man, although iuſtlie angrie, would bee appeaſed by ſuch a bloudie &amp; barbarous meanes? How were they blinded that thought one ſinne vvas a remedie for an other, &amp; that ſo hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous a ſinne as murther; that they purged ſinne, when they added ſin to ſinne, that they appeaſed Gods wrath when they moſt grievouſly kindled it?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Secondly for cure of this ſo great an evill, namely ſinne, they ſent vs to a ſuppoſed power in our ſelues, whereby we are able, if we pleaſe, to ſhake of all ſinne, yea vtterly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer the leaſt evill motions and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:102:34"/>of the minde as we haue heard<note n="*" place="margin">Char. Sect. 4.</note> before, and ſo inſteed of healing ſin thruſt vs into one of the greateſt ſins in the world, namely pride &amp; ſelfe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. Hence came that ſaying that went for a principle amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note n="r" place="margin">Vnuſqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que fortune ſuae faber.</note> that <hi>every mon was the forger of his owne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> that is, had power to frame and ſhape his owne ſtate and condition, &amp; to make himſelfe good or bad, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py or miſerable. So<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ovid. de Ponto eleg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ad Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manicum.</note> one flatters a great man. <hi>The Gods grant thee l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng life, for as for other things thou wilt giue them to thy ſelfe;</hi> and<note n="t" place="margin">Horat, ep. 18. lib. 1.</note> another flatters him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the ſame effect, ſaying, <hi>It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that I pray to Iupiter for long life and riches, for as for a good mind and vertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, I will giue that to my ſelfe.</hi> Neither are wee to thinke that theſe were only Poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call floriſhes, ſith the beſt Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers in their moſt ſerious diſcourſes and meditations affirme &amp; maintaine as much or rather more ſometimes.<note n="u" place="margin">Ariſt. Eth.</note> 
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> layeth this for a grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that <hi>both vertue and vice are in our power, or elſe we were neither to bee praiſed for well doing, nor diſpraiſed for ill doing:</hi> &amp;<note n="x" place="margin">Cie de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura Deoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lib. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> moſt profanely a voucheth, <hi>that wee truly &amp; iuſtly glory of our vertue, which we would never doe, if it were the gift of God,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:102:34"/>and not a thing of our owne.</hi> And<note n="y" place="margin">Sen. ep 31</note> 
                  <hi>Seneca</hi> is angry with thoſe that trouble the Gods with their prayers that they might be happy, ſaying withall, <hi>make thy ſelfe happy,</hi> as if he had ſaide. It is a matter in thine own power, what nee deſt thou be beholden to God for it? Nay<note n="z" place="margin">Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ep. 54.</note> hee goeth farther and tels vs, that <hi>in ſome reſpect, man hath the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of God himſelfe; ſith God is happy by the benefit of nature, but that man is happy by his ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e good hushanding of his minde,</hi> being indifferent liable to felicitie or miſery: that is, God is happy of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, but a wiſe and vertuous man by election and choice, for as much as whereas he might be either miſerable or happy, he by his free choiſe &amp; wiſe managing of his will makes himſelfe happy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To conclude<note n="a" place="margin">Senec. de vita beata c. 8.</note> he affirmes that one principall ſtep and degree vnto happineſſe is <hi>for a man to admire him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that is, to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ate vpon his owne excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10 But alas what poore comfort is there in all this. For firſt, ſo far of is it that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath any ſuch power to ſhake of ſinne, as hee is of himſelfe in irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediable bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage vnto it, as hath<note n="b" place="margin">Chap. 2. Sect. 8.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready beene declared, neither is hee
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:102:35"/>naught by ill education, or cuſtome, but by birth, or rather before his birth, as ſhall God willing appeare<note n="c" place="margin">Chap. 6. Sect. 4.1.</note> hereafter: ſo that to bid a man not to ſin, is to bid him not to eate when he is hungry, not to drinke when hee is thirſty, not to ſleepe when hee is drowſie, and overwatched, or rather indeed, to bid him not be hungry, not to be thirſty, not to be ſleepy or drow ſie; yea it is al one, as to bid water not to moiſten, fire not to heate, the ſea not to ebbe or flow, the ſunne not to moue, ſith he can no more of himſelfe forbeare to ſinne, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe creatures can ſuſpend ſuch their natural actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and motions.</p>
               <p n="11">11 Yea not only is this remedy al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vaine, but here vnder colour and ſhew of remedy, is there moſt deadlie poiſon miniſtred vnto vs. Being dead lie ſicke we are made beleeue wee are hoale, being by nature<note n="d" place="margin">Eph 2.3.</note> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle tels vs the children of wrath, and<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal 51.7.</note> as the kingly Prophet ſaith, formed and conceived in ſinne, we are tolde, that we may chuſe whether we will be guilty of ſin, or no, and that ſin comes only of ill cuſtome; being moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable bond-flaues, wee are borne in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:102:35"/>hand that we are free men, or might be free men if wee woulde our ſelues, the falſhood whereof hath been ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed before; having iuſt occaſion to hang downe our heades we are coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled to beare them aloft, &amp; to looke bigge, and whereas we ſhould be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of our ſelues, &amp; loath our ſelues we are taught to admire our ſelues &amp; doate vpon our ſelues, which is the very high way to make vs incapable of mercy and favour. For as<note n="f" place="margin">Aug. deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio lib. 3.</note> S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> well ſaith, <hi>What can be more vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of mercy than prowde miſery?</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he makes himſelfe vnworthy of pitty, that ſtands vpon high &amp; prowd tearmes, when nothing can releeue him, but pitty. <hi>The diſſembling of miſerie,</hi> ſaith<note n="g" place="margin">Ber. ſerm. quodam.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard, ſhuts out mercie: and they ſhall never be accepted as worthy, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume they are worthy.</hi> Many in regard of this life haue periſhed without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, becauſe in their ſtoutneſſe they would not bee beholden vnto mercie. It were eaſie to giue inſtances hereof both in ancient and later times, but generality herein is ſufficient It muſt be humiliation and ſubmiſſion, that muſt procure offendours favour; not preſumption or peremptory ſtanding
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:102:36"/>vpon their iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a bad cauſe. To counſell the malefactour to plead his innocency when his capitall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is notorious and manifeſt, what is it elſe, but to helpe him the ſooner to the gallowes? Whereas perhaps by confeſſing himſelfe guilty, and ſuing for a pardon in time, hee might haue beene acquitted. And thus wee haue ſeene that all the remedies which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon hath beene able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe againſt our miſery, that is, againſt the evils which we ſuffer, or the evils which we doe, againſt our paines and puniſhmentes, or againſt our ſinnes which are the cauſe therof, are either vaine and ridiculous, or impious and pernicious.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> That true religion revealed vnto vs by Gods worde only diſcovereth vnto vs the cauſe of our miſerie.</head>
               <p n="1">1 HOw ignorant the naturall man is touching the cauſe of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, hath ſufficientlie appeared by things already ſpoken. It remaineth that wee nowe ſhewe the true cauſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:102:36"/>thereof, which only<note n="a" place="margin">Gen c. 3.</note> Gods word no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifies vnto vs: and that is, that our firſt parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> beeing created by God and placed in Paradiſe in a moſt happy and pleaſant ſtate of life, only reſtrained from taſting of the fruit of one only tree, to vveete the tree of the knowledge of good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, as a triall of their ſubiection and loyalty, by the Divels ſuggeſtion Gods deadly enemy &amp; theirs, preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to eate thereof, and ſo loſt the loue, and favour of God, and incurred his diſpleaſure and indignation, and conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly became ſubiect to al mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery &amp; calamity not only in this life, but alſo in the life to come.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It may ſeeme that this offence was not ſo hainous nor deſerved ſuch ſevere puniſhment. But we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that many and grievous iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties yea abominations lurked in this fact. For firſt of all, God having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly told the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that whenſoever they ſhoulde taſte of this forbidden fruite, they ſhould die the death, that is, they ſhould ſurely die, they harkening to the ſerpent telling them the contrary make God a lyer, yea take the Devils word before his. Now how great a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:102:37"/>wickednes this was, the ſimpleſt may eaſily perceiue. Secondly here vvas great ingratitude and vnthankfulnes. The Devill tels them that God had dealt craftily with them in telling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there was ſuch daunger in eating of that fruit, whereas indeede it had that vertue to make them equall to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and therefore in pollicie he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bade them to taſte of it. Which neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily argues that they were malecon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent with their preſent eſtate, as if God had dealt niggardly with them, and had not beſtowed ſo much vpon them as hee might haue done, and ſo in effect, that the Devill would by his counſell and adviſe do more for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then God had done or woulde doe. Thirdly &amp; principally, here was high treaſon againſt the moſt high, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with deteſtable blaſphemie. For they eating of the forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fruit, becauſe as the Devill informed them therby they ſhould be equall to God, manifeſtly ſhewed that they diſdained to be Gods vnderlings, and to hold a happines from him by inferiority and dependancie, and would be happy ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, and of themſelues without being any way beholding to God for
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:102:37"/>the ſame. Now when the ſubiect deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth homage and fealty to the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, the Creature to the Creator, man to God, what can it bee but high treaſon, yea higheſt treaſon as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt the higheſt? Beſides it could bee no leſſe than abhominable blaſphemy, that a mortal man ſhould ſo much as admit a thought to make himſelfe equal to the immortal God, much more to deſire it, yea to attempt it.</p>
               <p n="3">3 And yet further this doth not a little aggravat their ſin, that they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had abſolute power not to ſinne. To expreſſe this pointe, I had rather vſe Saint Auguſtines wordes then mine own. <hi>If,</hi> ſaith<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> de ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitat Dei li. 14. c. 15.</note> he, <hi>any man thinke that Adams condemnation was either too heavy, or vniuſt: ſurely hee knowes not howe to weigh the matter, namely how great the iniquity of ſinning was, vvhen there was ſo great eaſines not to ſin.</hi> And a little after, <hi>Where there is great puniſhment threatned for diſobedience, and the matter comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by the creatour to be obeyed, ſo eaſie, who can ſufficiently declare how great a wickedneſſe it is not to obey in a matter ſo eaſie, &amp; where there is ſo great power to obey and ſo greate danger for not obeying?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:102:38"/>4 I omit many other conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which might farther aggravat the greatneſſe of our firſt parents ſin. But that which hath beene alreadie ſaide may ſuffice. Only this I thought good not to omit, that it may be replied by ſome, that howe great ſoever their perſonall offence were, yet what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is it that their poſterity ſhoulde beare the ſmart thereof, and that in ſo hard meaſure, as wee ſee and feele by common experience, that they doe? The anſwere is eaſie, that <hi>Adam</hi> had either happineſſe or miſerie in his owne hands, not onely for himſelfe but for all his: and therefore by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king himſelfe miſerable willinglie, I meane, at leaſt, willingly doing the thing that iuſtly made him miſerable hee alſo iuſtly drewe miſerie vpon all his. We ſee that even humane iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice puniſheth the children for the offenſe of the fathers. He that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits treaſon not only dyeth himſelfe for it, but brings miſerie vpon all his children, who by his offenſe looſe all their goods and lands that otherwiſe ſhould haue deſcended vnto them, as alſo if the parties ſo offending bee of ſuch quality and ranke, their nobility
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:102:38"/>and advantages of birth, and paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. Again, we as commonly kill the yong foxes, wolues, and ſuch like ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous and noiſome beaſts as the old, although as yet they haue done no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall harme, becauſe we knowe they are of the ſame nature, that the olde are, and lacke not malice but time to hurt and deſtroy. Much more therfore may God, that more hates malignitie of nature in man, than man doeth in beaſtes, manifeſt his wrath againſt mankinde even in their infancie, knovving that the roote and ſeede of all evill lurkes in them from the wombe, yea in the wombe, and that the poiſon of ſinne and wickedneſſe is even incorporated into their eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. And this is the cauſe of all thoſe miſeries and extremities which many times wee ſee yong children to endure. The ignoraunce of which point drewe the Gentiles out of the Church, and hereticks in the Church into that ridiculous errour * before ſpecified,<note place="margin">Chap. 3. Sect. 3.</note> that mens ſoules had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſome foule fault in heaven for the which they were ſent into bodies here on earth to doe penance for the ſame. Now man having thus vvilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:102:39"/>ſeperated himſelfe from God his Creator, and the onely author of his happineſſe, it is no marvaile if he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſubiect to all kinde of miſerie. <hi>This was,</hi> ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">Aug. de ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit Dei lib. 6 cap. 13.</note> S. Auguſtine, <hi>a perverſe haughtineſſe, to forſake that originall cauſe wherevnto only the ſoule ought to cleaue, &amp; after a ſort to become his owne originall,</hi> that is, to leaue God, and goe about to be his owne God, and to be happy without being beholding to God for it. And a little after, <hi>Man by affecting to be more then he was, is now leſſe then hee was: and while he made choice to be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of himſelfe, forſook him that only coulde be ſufficient for him.</hi> And<note n="d" place="margin">Ambro. de Elia &amp; iein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mio cap 4.</note> S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> brings in God expoſtulating &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonning the matter with man after his fall, thus, <hi>Didſt thou thinke to bee like vnto vs? therefore ſith thou wouldſt be what thou waſt not, thou haſt ceaſed to be what thou waſt.</hi> And<note n="c" place="margin">Bernard. tractat. de gratia &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bero arbit.</note> S. <hi>Bernard</hi> verie ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſeth this point, ſaith he, <hi>they</hi> (to wit our firſt parents) <hi>which woulde needes be their owne, became not only their owne, but the Devils alſo,</hi> that is, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels ſlaues, held in bondage by him at his pleaſure, as<note n="f" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.36.</note> the Apoſtle ſpeakes. This was a wofull alteration that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who was the ſonne of God, while hee
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:102:39"/>would be Gods equall, ceaſed not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be his ſonne, but alſo his ſervant and became the ſervant of ſinne and Sathan And what a miſerie it is to be in bondage vnto ſin, yea what an evil ſin of it ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe is,<note place="margin">Chapt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. ſect. 5. &amp; 6.</note> hath * already beene ſufficiently declared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> The true remedies which Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion affordeth againſt the firſt kind of mans miſerie, that is, the evils of paine.</head>
               <p n="1">1 VVHat poore &amp; cold comfort naturall me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea the beſt of naturall men, and as it were the flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of them haue beene able to finde out againſt mans double miſerie, namely the evils of paine, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils of fault, that is, the evils which he ſuffereth, and the evils which hee doth, ſufficiently appeareth by things * before ſpoken.<note place="margin">Chap. 5. throughout.</note> Let vs now ſee what better reliefe and remedy true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on yeeldeth vs in that behalfe. As for the evils of faulte, that is, ſinne the cauſe of all evils of paine, the remedy that Chriſtianity affordeth vs, is free pardon of our ſinnes and reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:102:40"/>to God by faith in Ieſus Chriſt. As for the evils of paine, they are of two ſorts: either of temporary paine in this world; or of eternall paine in the world to come. The remedies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the former, namely temporary paines in this world, are the gratious change of them vnto many profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vſes: the remedie againſt the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, namely eternall paines in the world to come is all one with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie againſt the evils of faulte, or ſinnes. For the ſame mercy of God which frees vs from ſinne, doth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all free vs from the eternall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due vnto ſinne, and therefore I will ioine them both in one in the next Chapter. For howſoever the ſtrict lawes of order require I ſhoulde firſt ſpeake of the evils of fault as the cauſe of all evill of paine, and then of the evils of paine that proceede there of: that is, firſt of ſinne; and then of the puniſhments for ſinne: yet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the evils of paine, that is, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments for ſinne, ſpecially tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary puniſhments, whereof I only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate here, that is, the miſeries and afflictions of this life, are more ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our nature then the evils of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:102:40"/>fault, that is, than ſinnes themſelues, as alſo becauſe they be the leſſer evils of the two, howſoever more felt, I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther regarding the conveniencie of matter, than curioſity of methode, wil ſpeake of them firſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The firſt conſolation then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all worldly miſeries, is this, that whereas of themſelues they are tokens of Gods wrath &amp; diſpleaſure, and a part of his iuſtice vpon ſinners beginning in this world, and ending in the worlde to come, or rather to ſpeake properly never ending, and are a taſt, and as it were fore-runners of hell torments; now cleane contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, vnto all that are in Chriſt, and by faith in Chriſt ſtand reconciled vnto God, whereof by Gods aſſiſtance wee ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare more at large in the next Chapter, they are ſignes and pledges of his loue and favour. A ſtrange alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that they which before vvere heralds of defiance, ſhoulde now bee meſſengers of peace, and proclaimers of amity and loue: yet that the caſe thus ſtandeth, is manifeſt by Gods ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe teſtimonies. <hi>My ſonne,</hi> ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">Prov. 3 11. &amp; 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> that is God by <hi>Salomon, deſpiſe not the chaſtiſement of the Lord, nor be wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:102:41"/>of his correction: For the Lord correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth every one that he loueth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as a father doth the ſonne to whom he wiſheth good.</hi> And the<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 12.5. &amp; 6. Verſ. 7. &amp; 8.</note> Apoſtle repeating it almoſt word for word, * inferreth out of it by neceſſary conſequence, that affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction beeing the badge of all Gods ſonnes, therefore they that taſted not of it were baſtardes and not ſonnes. And ſo<note n="c" place="margin">Apoc. 3.19.</note> Chriſt himſelfe profeſſeth to the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> that hee dealt thus with all that he loved, namelie that he exerciſed them with affliction <hi>As many,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as I loue, I rebuke, and chaſtiſe.</hi> Thus all afflictions &amp; worldly croſſes to the faithful are ſo many to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, ſent from heaven to earth from God to man, from Chriſt to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, to aſſure vs of loue and favor; &amp; who would not be glad, nay prowd to receiue loue tokens from an earthlie king, how much more from the king of heaven?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Secondly it is to be conſidered that theſe evils of paine are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comfortable for teſtification, but alſo proficable in operation, &amp; bring forth moſt notable effects in the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. So ſaith<note n="d" place="margin">Pſ 119. v. 67. &amp; 71.</note> 
                  <hi>David, Before I was affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, went aſtray: but now doe I keepe thy
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:102:41"/>commandements.</hi> And againe, <hi>It is good for mee that I haue heene in trouble, that thereby I might learne thy ſtatutes.</hi> And<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 12.10.</note> the holy Apoſtle is bold to ſay, that <hi>God chaſtiſeth vs for our good, that wee may be made partakers of his holineſſe: novve all chaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the preſent ſeemeth not to be ioyous, but grievous; but afterward it brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the quiet fruit of righteouſnes to them that are exerciſed thereby.</hi> And<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.3.4.5.</note> S. <hi>Paule</hi> goeth yet further, affirming that affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to thoſe that are in Chriſt, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter matter not only of profit, but alſo of glorie. <hi>Therefore,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>Wee glory in tribulation, knowing that tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bringeth patience, and patience experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and experience hope, and hope maketh not aſhamed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 And hence it is that Divines reach that afflictions to ſpeak proper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, vnto the godly are not puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts but ought to bee tearmed by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name So ſaith<note n="g" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in 1. Corin. hom. 28.</note> S. <hi>Chryſoſtome; wee are not puniſhed, but inſtructed: ſo that our affliction is for admonition, not for condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; for Phyſicke, not for torment; for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, not for vexatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> That is in a word, all our tribulations are for inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not for deſtruction.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The very heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s could ſee that
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:102:42"/>ſome benefit did grow from trouble &amp; miſerie. As firſt, that it was a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyſon againſt the danngers of too much proſperity, as pride, riot, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnes, and the like, which haue been the bane of many men.<note n="h" place="margin">Herod. l. 3</note> 
                  <hi>Amaſis</hi> king of Aegypt deſired that he &amp; his might taſt of adverſity, and vnderſtanding of the incomparable proſperity of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licrates</hi> Prince of <hi>Samos,</hi> who was ſo luckie in all his affaires, that when of purpoſe he had caſt his ſignet that had in it an Emerald of wondrous value, into the ſea, he had it brought to him again in the belly of a fiſh that ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after was ſerved in at his table, hee preſently renounced the amitie and league that had beene long betweene them, ſuſpecting that ſome great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe would befall him, wherein hee would be loath to ſhare with him: as indeede it fell out; for being craftily trained into the hands of his enemies he was crucified aliue. Yea<note n="i" place="margin">Iuvenal. Satyr. 6.</note> the verie Poet obſerved and complained,<note n="*" place="margin">Heu pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur longae pacis mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaevior armis Luxuria in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbit &amp;c.</note> that <hi>in his time they were even ſicke with eaſe &amp; proſperity; &amp; more plagued with peace, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ever they had beene with wars.</hi> And<note n="k" place="margin">Sen. ep 52.</note> the Philoſopher wittily ſaies of <hi>Hanniball</hi> effeminated by eaſe &amp; delicacie, that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:102:42"/>
                  <hi>he overcame by armes:</hi> but was himſelfe overcome by vices:<note n="l" place="margin">Idem ep. 19.115.</note> who alſo notes, that this was the ſpoile of Mecoenas, and not only of him, but generally of very many who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proſperity brought to a madnes of vanity &amp; luxury. Againe they ſaw that ſometime croſſes occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned encreaſe of iudgement, and bred an experimentall knowledge which was not a little to be eſteemed. So<note n="m" place="margin">Chion in ep. quadam</note> 
                  <hi>Chion</hi> gaue harty thankes to the croſſe windes that kept him at Byz a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium againſt his will: becauſe by this meanes he grew acquainted with Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon arrived there during his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained ſtay, &amp; greatly benefited him ſelfe by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference &amp; intercourſe with him. And<note n="n" place="margin">Plutarch. Apopht. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum &amp; Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perat.</note> 
                  <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> being baniſhed by his vnkinde country, was wont to ſay to his followers, <hi>Except we had been vndone we had beene vndone.</hi> So much did hee thinke hee had gained by his baniſhment; becauſe he thereby grew in favour with the king of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and was greatly advaunced and enriched by him.</p>
               <p n="6">6 How much more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians picke profite out of adverſitie, yea ſuch profit as the blinde Gentils never dreamed of? For all that they
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:102:43"/>gained or poſſibly could gaine by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, was but a civill &amp; morall wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their outward behaviour in this preſent worlde and in regard of men: But the Chriſtian taketh out farre higher leſſons from adverſity.</p>
               <p n="7">7 For firſt hereby they learne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the world, which is no ſmall matter. For how dangerous a thing the loue of the worlde is appeares by this that it is incompatible with the loue of God, &amp; cannot ſtand with it. <hi>Know yee not,</hi> ſaith<note n="o" place="margin">Iam. 44,</note> S. <hi>Iames, that the friendſhip of the worlde, is enmitie vvith God? Whoſoever then will be n friend of the world, becommeth the enemie of God.</hi> And ſaith<note n="p" place="margin">Ioh. 1.2. verſ. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Iohn, See that yee loue not the world, nor the things of the worlde: if any man loue the world, the loue of the father is not in him.</hi> Thus we ſee that of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wee muſt bee out of loue with the world, if we woulde bee in loue vvith God: enemies with the world, or elſe we cannot be friends with God. The contempt of the world then toucheth vs as neerely as our verie ſalvation, neither can there bee any ſalvation without it. But now what can ſo well teach vs the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt of the world, as
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:102:43"/>experience of the vanities and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the world? It is then a ſpeciall token of Gods loue and favour when he by afflictions &amp; croſſes makes the worlde bitter and vnſavorie vnto vs, therby to waine vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. As mothers or nurſes when they would weyne ſucking children do vſe to annoint their teates with worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woode or ſome other bitter thing, thereby to make them weary of ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to leaue the ſweet for avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the bitter, ſo God when hee woulde weyne his children from the loue of the world, by adverſities and croſſes maketh it bitter and vnſavory to them, leaſt they ſhould too deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſucke in the poyſon thereof, yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſucke themſelues to death, as car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall men that liue in all proſperity &amp; iolity vſually doe, according to that ſaying of wiſe<note n="q" place="margin">Pro. 1.32.</note> 
                  <hi>Salomon, that the eaſe of fooles killeth them, and the proſperity of the fooliſh deſtroieth them;</hi> by fools meaning the wicked, whom proſperity makes wanton and fooliſh, depriving them of all ſpirituall vnderſtanding, if they had any, or elſe keeping them from ever having any. And this as<note n="r" place="margin">Ier. 48.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieremie</hi> or rather the Lord by <hi>Ieremie</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:102:44"/>was the over throw and ruine of the <hi>Moabits,</hi> becauſe<note n="r" place="margin">Ierem. 48. ver. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Moab was quiet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from his youth, and ſate vpon the Lees, nor was powred out from veſſell into veſſel, nor lead into captivitie.</hi> Thus a flattering world poyſoneth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but a frowning world preſerveth: a flattering world defileth, a frowning world purifieth: in a word, a flattering world damneth a frowning world ſaveth. And who woulde not bee content to haue the world his ſtepmother, ſo that hee may haue God his father? And how neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary it is that the world ſhould bee a ſtep-mother vnto vs that wee might not over loue it, appears by that gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſpeech of<note n="ſ" place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> an ancient divine; <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the world is ſtormie and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous, and yet wee loue it, what ſhould we doe if it were calme? How wouldſt thou imbrace and cole a beautifull worlde, that makeſt ſo much of a fowle and deformed world? howe greedily wouldeſt thou gather the roſes of it, that canſt hardly hold thy hands from the thornes of it?</hi> That is, how ſhould we doare vpon the world, if it were an indulgent mother; that can ſcarſe forbeare to loue it, being a curſt ſtepmother?</p>
               <p n="8">8 Beſides the miſeries of this life
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:102:44"/>do ſerue notably to mortifie our luſts, and concupiſcenſes. For, as proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is oile to kindle them: ſo adverfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is water to coole and quench the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Hereby anger is mitigated, luſt aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, pride deiected, and in a word, all inordinate affections &amp; deſires recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Hence it is that affliction in holy ſcripture is often tearmed a fornace, yea a fiery fornace: becauſe it purgeth out our corruptions, and maketh ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration betweene the golde and the droſſe of our ſoules, betweene our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and our vertues. And hence it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that our very enimies are our ſervants and procure our good, when they ſeeme moſt to hurt &amp; annoy vs. <hi>Wouldſt thou know how this comes to paſſe,</hi> ſaith<note n="t" place="margin">Auguſtin. de tempor. ſermo 78,</note> S. <hi>Auguſtine? Why they ſo ſerue vs as files and hammers ſerue gold; as milles ſerue wheate, as ovens ſerue for the baking &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king of bread, finally as ſtraw, and chaffe in the fornace ſerveth gold, where the chaffe is co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſumed to nothing, but the gold remaineth yea is made better then it was, being purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereby.</hi> Which reſemblances, if wee well marke them, are very proper &amp; excellent. For one would thinke that the file by galling, &amp; the hammer by beating ſhould marre the golde; &amp; yet
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:102:45"/>they both better it: one would thinke that the chaffe which nouriſheth the fire in the Goldſmiths fornace ſhould be hurtfull to the gold, as alſo the mil to the wheate which it grindeth to powder, and the oven to the loaues which it burneth and ſcorcheth with ſo violent heare; and yet are all theſe things brought to their perfection by the things which in ſhew ſo much an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy them: gold by the file, hammer, &amp; burning chaffe; wheare by the mill, &amp; loaues by the oven; And ſo a true Chriſtian is purified and perfected by the things that threate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, namely by croſſes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffictions.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Neither doe the miſeries of this life only mortifie our vices, but alſo either breed, or at leaſt increaſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent vertues in vs, as hath in part * alreadie beene touched. And therfore<note n="u" place="margin">In this chap. ſect. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 2. Corinth 4 verſ. 16.</note> the bleſſed Apoſtle ioineth both theſe benefits together, ſaying that <hi>while our outward man periſheth, our inward man is renued thereby:</hi> meaning, that as afflictions do weaken and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume our naturall life; ſo they ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then &amp; further our ſpiritual life. And ô happy loſſe that cauſeth ſuch gain, ô happy ſmart that cauſeth ſuch eaſe,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:102:45"/>yea ô happy death that cauſeth ſuch a life. Thus we ever come out of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we were before. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we haue a notable reſemblance, or rather a type &amp; prefiguration in the children of Iſraels bondage in Aegypt recorded by<note n="x" place="margin">Geneſ 15. ver. 13. &amp; 14</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> in his holy hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. God fore-told that they ſhould be ſlaues in Aegypt for many yeares, and ſuffer great affliction there: but yet that in the end they ſhould come out of it, and that with advantage, namely with gold, ſilver, iewels, and far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſubſtance the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had when they went thither, as<note n="y" place="margin">Exod 12. v. 35.36, &amp;</note> the event indeed manifeſtly ſhewed. Even ſo it fareth with all true Chriſtians; they muſt go into Aegypt, and endure bondage there, that is, they muſt ſuffer many troubles and miſeries in this life: but they ſhall come out of them in better caſe then they were before. But what? doe Gods children come out of their troubles and adverſities with more gold, and ſilver, or with better appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell then they had before, as the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites did out of Aegypt? No ſurely: but yet with far more pretious things then golde, or ſilver, or gorgeous at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, namely with more knowledge,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:102:46"/>with more wiſedome, with more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, with more humility, with more zeale, with more conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory life, aed more longing after the life to come, which is eternall. Now what goodly treaſures are theſe, and how farre more pretious then thoſe which the Iſraelites brought out of Aegypt after their long bondage and manifold grievances there?<note n="z" place="margin">Tertull de p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia. c. 7</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith ſtrangly, <hi>Let the whole world periſh ſo that I may gaine patience.</hi> If hee helde that one vertue of patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce worth the buying at ſo high a rate, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the loſſe of the whole world: how much more ſhould we thinke ſo many other vertues together with it, worth the buying with ſome ſhort &amp; tranſitory adverſities and croſſes of the world?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Laſt of all a true Chriſtian hath by the benefit of his holy profeſſion this notable comfort againſt the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of this preſent life, that making ſuch religious vſes thereof, as hath beene ſaid, he is acquitted of eternall miſeries of the life to come. So<note n="a" place="margin">Luc. 16. ver. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaven tels the rich glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton in hel, <hi>Remember,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that thou receivedſt good thing in this life &amp; Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous evill: therefore now is he comforted, at
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:102:46"/>thou art tormented.</hi> And, ſaith<note n="b" place="margin">1 Corinth. 11. verſ. 32.</note> S <hi>Paul, When we are iudged of the Lord, wee are corrected to the ende we ſhould not be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the world.</hi> Thus, if God cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect vs, the Divell ſhall haue nothing to doe with vs. And how happy would the ſonne thinke himſelfe, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving deſerved to bee ſtrangled by the hangman, might ſcape by whipping, and the whipping too referred to his owne father? Thus the evils of paine or the afflictions of this life to a true Chriſtian miniſter many comforts, &amp; yeeld them many benefits, ſo that we ſhould rather deſire them, then bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermuch afraid of them, or diſmaide with them, Therefore<note n="c" place="margin">Bern in Cant. ſer. 42</note> S. <hi>Bernards</hi> meditation is excellent touching this point, that <hi>God is never more angry then when he is not angry,</hi> that is, when hee ſheweth no tokens of his diſpleaſure by correcting vs. For although this may ſeeme to be mercy and favor, yet ſaith he <hi>I will none of this mercy; this mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is worſe then all wrath or anger.</hi> To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, let vs make ſuch holy vſes of the miſeries which we endure in this life, as hath beene ſhewed; and they ſhall ſerue vs for an acquittance of al miſeries, and torments in the life to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:102:47"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> That the Chriſtian religion only affordeth vs true remedy againſt the ſecond kinde of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, that is the evils which wee doe, or our ſinnes.</head>
               <p n="1">1 THAT the greateſt evils in this worlde, are the evils which wee doe, that is, our ſinnes hath been<note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 2. Sect 5.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſufficiently declared:<note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 5. Sect. 7. &amp; 8.</note> as alſo that the beſt remedies that naturall men, though never ſo wiſe &amp; learned haue beene able to deviſe againſt the ſame, are of no force, nay that they are raſher poyſons then medicines. Let vs now ſee what helpes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts Divinity and true religion will afford vs againe the ſame.</p>
               <p n="2">2 And firſt wee muſt admit it for a ground that neither our ſelues, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other like vnto our ſelues, (that is, meere men) can remedy this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; that is, deliver vs from ſinne. For both we and they are ſo captivated &amp; enthralled therevnto, that wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly free our ſelues from it, as hath beene<note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 2. Sect. 8.1 &amp; Chap. 6. Sect 4.</note> before declared, wherevnto we may adde that golden
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:102:47"/>ſpeech of<note n="a" place="margin">Bern. trac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> de gratia &amp; libero arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard,</hi> that <hi>although power were given to mans will to ſtand &amp; not fal: yet not a power to riſe againe, if it did fall. For it is not ſo eaſie for a man to come out of a pit, as to fall into a pit.</hi> It is in vain then to ſeeke helpe either from our ſelues or others like vnto our ſelues, in this caſe, namely againſt ſinne.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Here mans ſtate being both ſo miſerable, and alſo ſo remediles, God ſteps in to ſtelpe him, when hee was not able to helpe himſelfe, and after an incomprehenſible manner ſo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered mercy and iuſtice one with the other, that neither ſinne ſhoulde bee ſimply pardoned, nor yet the ſinner be condemned, but that both the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe ſhould be puniſhed, and yet the offender abſolved. This may ſeeme ſtrange, and indeed is moſt ſtrange, &amp; therefore<note n="b" place="margin">Rom 16. ver. 25. &amp; Coloſ. 1. verſ, 20.</note> in the ſcriptures is called <hi>a miſtery,</hi> yea <hi>a hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſtery,</hi> yea <hi>a miſtery hidden from the beginning of the world vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the fulneſſe of time,</hi> that is, vntill the time appointed by God in his infinit wiſdome for the revelation thereof. This miſtery in few wordes is, that God ſent his only ſonne Ieſus Chriſt into the worlde to take vpon him the nature of man in the wombe, and of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:102:48"/>the ſubſtance of the virgin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mary, and in this nature to preach all truth and to fulfill all righteouſneſſe in his life, and afterwardes to ſuffer a moſt both ignominious and painful death vpon the croſſe, that by his bloud he might waſh away mans ſins, &amp; ſo reconcile to himſelfe all thoſe that by faith em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced him as their redeemer, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues that moſt glorious and ſoveraigne ſacrifice of his death and paſſion. The ſumme whereof,<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 3.16.</note> the Evangeliſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehends in theſe few but golden words; <hi>So God loved the world, that he gaue his only begotten ſonne, to the end that whoſoever beleeved in him, ſhould not periſh, but haue life everlaſting.</hi> For the better vnderſtanding wherof we muſt obſerue that the humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in Chriſt is not a diſtinct and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall perſon by it ſelfe, as <hi>Peter, Iohn,</hi> and ſuch like: but ſo vnited to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature that did aſſume it, as they both make but one perſon, ſo that all that is in it, is truely ſaid to be Gods, and al that was done by it; to be done by God;<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> his bloud was Gods bloud, his death Gods death, &amp;c: which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily: implyeth the perfection of all his actions, beeing the actions of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:102:48"/>him that was God as well as man, and both God and man in one perſon. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly we muſt note that all that hee did or ſuffered in his humane nature thus vnited to the divine, he did and ſuffred for vs, that we might haue the benefite of it: he tooke our evils vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, our ſinnes and death due to our ſins; and imparted his good things to vs, his innocency, obedience, holines and righteouſneſſe, &amp; finally his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings partly in his life time, but principally at his death vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe his humiliation is our exaltation, his condemnation our abſolution, his death our life.</p>
               <p n="4">4 This courſe was moſt effectuall and availeable in this caſe, yea in the apprehenſion of man only of force &amp; poſſibilitie to remedy this branch of our miſerie, namely our ſinnes, and condemnation for ſinne. For firſt,<note n="e" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in prior ep. ad Timoth. hom. 7.</note> he that is to reconcile perſons that are at variance &amp; difference one with the other, muſt haue intereſt in both; elſe is he vnfit to reconcile them, and bring them friends: wherefore God and man being at variance, it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite that he which ſhoulde recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile them ſhoulde be both God &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:102:49"/>Againe man having ſinned, iuſtice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired that man ſhould be puniſhed, &amp; having ſinned vnto death ſhould be puniſhed with death; but now a meer ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s death could not ſalue the matter for as formerly hath been ſhewed, the death of one ſinner cannot pay the debt and death of another, every ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner owing a death for himſelfe. And beſides, he that was to deliver others from the danger of penalty and death was not only to ſuffer death, but alſo to vanquiſh &amp; overco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e death which a meere ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could never haue don God could not dy, &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could not recover himſelfe, when he ſhould dy: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Mediatour was to be man to ſuffer death, and God to vanquiſh death Thus as<note n="f" place="margin">Anſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. tract cur Deus homo</note> a Divine of mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle times ſweetly ſaith, <hi>Sith ſuch a ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction was requiſite as none but God could make, &amp; none but man was bound to make: he that was to make it, was to bee both God and man.</hi> Thus our Chriſtian religion only directs vs to the meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is poſſibility of ſaving vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſins, and hence it is,<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 1. v. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that Chriſt had the name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> that is, of <hi>a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> as he that only could and would do this ſo great a worke.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:102:49"/>5 And that he as well would do it, as could do it, yea therefore only was incarnated and ſuffered death that he might do it, is moſt evident.<note n="h" place="margin">Cyp. de I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolor. vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt was made that which man was, that man might be made that which Chriſt was.</hi> And, as<note n="i" place="margin">Bernard. in vigilia nativit. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini.</note> Bernard ſaith, <hi>why was the ſon of God made the ſonne of man, but that the ſonnes of men might be made the ſonnes of God? Sure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Gregor. homi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 34. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vangel.</note> 
                  <hi>this cannot but yeeld man boldnes with God, that God himſelfe is become man.</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Auguſt in Pſal. 148.</note> There is no cauſe nowe why man ſhould doubt of living for ever, ſith God hath died for him. For ſhal not he liue for ever, for whome hee died that liues for ever? Verily it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo ſtrange that mortall man ſhould liue, as that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he immortal God ſhould die, ſpecially ſince this death of the ſon of God was vniuſt &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe in reſpect of himſelfe, and therefore muſt needs be available for ſome others, as<note n="m" place="margin">Auguſt de temp. ſerm. 101.</note> S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaies, <hi>Death could not be conquered but by death, therefore Chriſt ſuffered death that an vniuſt death might overcome iuſt death, and that he might deliver the guilty iuſtly, by dying for them vniuſtly.</hi> And thus<note n="n" place="margin">Auguſt. de verbis Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini ſecund Luca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; &amp; de temp. ſerm. 141.</note> 
                  <hi>by taking vpon him our puniſhment, without taking vpon him our fault; he hath diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:102:50"/>vs both of the puniſhment, and the fault.</hi> And that by good right,<note n="o" place="margin">Bernard. ad milites templi, c. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>ſith although becauſe he was ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he could die, yet becauſe he was iuſt, he ought not to haue died, &amp; he that had no cauſe to die for himſelfe, in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and equity ſhould not die for others vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably.</hi> Neither ſurely did hee, but to greateſt purpoſe, namely, that the ſonne of God dying for the ſonnes of men, the ſons of men might be made the ſonnes of God, as we heard before out of S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> yea that <hi>of bad ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts men might be made good ſonnes,</hi> as<note n="p" place="margin">Aug. ſer. 28</note> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh: and this glorious myſtery of our Saviours incarnation and paſſion muſt needes bring foorth glorious effects,<note n="q" place="margin">Anſel. in c <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. ep. ad Eph</note> 
                  <hi>this ſtrange and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable loue of God that his only ſonne ſhould die for vs,</hi> that <hi>a Lord ſhould die for ſervants, the creatour for the creature, God for man,</hi> this ſtrange loue I ſay, muſt needs be of ſtrange operation, as it is<note n="r" place="margin">Bern. feria 4. heb dom. paenolae.</note> 
                  <hi>even to make of ſinners iuſt men, of ſlaues brethren, of captiues fellow heires, and of baniſht perſons kings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 Why then ſhoulde our ſins diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may vs, if we be vnfainedly ſorrie for them, and by faith haue recourſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt that hath borne the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them? O let vs thinke vpon
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:102:50"/>this comfortable cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Auguſt. m Pſal. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. c. narrat. 2.</note> that <hi>Chriſt made our faults his faults, that hee might make his righteouſneſſe our righteouſneſſe.</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Iuſt. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr ad Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agnetum.</note> 
                  <hi>O ſweet exchange, o vnſearchable skill, that the vnrighteouſnes of many ſhould bee hidden in one that is righteous, &amp; the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of one ſhould cauſe many that are vnrighteous to be accounted righteous.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we bee not, nor cannot bee without ſinne, yet as long as our ſins are not imputed to vs, they cannot hurr vs. The princely prophet <hi>David</hi> as<note n="u" place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 32. c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rat. 2.</note> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> well obſerues, ſaies not <hi>they are happy that haue no ſinne,</hi> but <hi>whoſe ſinnes are covered. Surely if God haue covered our ſinnes, he will not ſee them; if he will not ſee them, he wil not examin the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; if he will not examine them, he will not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them.</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 119.</note> 
                  <hi>According to the groundes of our Chriſtian faith, they are accounted for no ſinners, to whome their ſinnes are not imputed, &amp;</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Idem de nuptiis &amp; concupiſe. cap 26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>not to be held guilty of ſinne is not to haue ſinne, or, to bee without ſinne.</hi> Do we fail in our obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the law of God &amp; many times break his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts? <hi>Why</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Idem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. lib 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cap. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>all the comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dements are the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> held to be kept, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all is pardoned that is not kept.</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Bernard in Cantic. ſerm 33 &amp; in An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nunciat Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riae ſerm</note> It is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſufficient righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe to haue our vnrighteouſnes forgiven, and to haue him only favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:102:51"/>to vs whome only wee haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended. True it is that that which is done cannot but be done, and yet not being imputed, it is all one, as if it had not beene done.</p>
               <p n="7">7 This plea muſt needs confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the Devil, and put him to ſilence. For<note n="b" place="margin">Bernard.</note> if <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne could make vs guilty ſhall not Chriſts righteouſnes much more make vs innocent? Shall there be more vertue in the ſeed of the firſt Adam, then in the bloud of the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Adam? Doubtleſſe the greateſt force and efficacy is ever in the greater and ſtronger agent, and therefore Chriſt is fat more able to ſaue then Adam to condemne, and why ſhould not wee haue righteouſnes from another, as well as wee had guiltineſſe from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?<note place="margin">1. Corinth. verſ. 1.</note> ſpecially ſith<note n="c" place="margin">p. 190.</note> Chriſt was made righteouſneſſe vnto vs by God the father: and ſhall not that righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be ours which was made over to vs, and made over by God himſelfe? Carnall generation from Adam ſhall never be of ſuch force to damne vs, as ſpirituall regeneration in Chriſt to ſaue vs. And if Sathan ſay vnto vs that a bad father ſoulde vs, wee may preſently anſwere that a good bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:102:51"/>hath ranſomed vs.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Finally, what could wee wiſh more?<note n="d" place="margin">An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elm. cur Deus homo lib<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> Being miſerable creatures, and not able to free our ſelues from the bondage of ſinne and Satan, God the father ſaies vnto every one of vs, take my ſonne and giue him for thee, and the ſonne himſelfe ſaith, take me &amp; redeeme thy ſelfe with me.<note n="e" place="margin">Idem in meditat.</note> What ſweeter entreatie can there bee, then to intreate the father in the ſonnes name, yea for his only begotten and moſt dearely beloued ſonnes ſake? By this kind of mediation many captiues haue been ſet free, many malefactors haue obtained their pardon, many that every houre looked for the ſtroak of death haue had their liues given them. O happy and thrice happy are they that are allowed this favorable and gratious acceſſe vnto the father in the name of his ſonne, &amp; ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plead thus, <hi>O Lord remember what a good ſonne hath ſuffered, and forget what a bad ſeruant hath done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9 There remaineth yet another ſingular conſolation againſt ſo great an evill, to wit ſinne, and that is, that God in his infinite wiſdome turneth our very ſinnes themſelues to our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:102:52"/>and advantage, ſo farre of is it that they ſhall condemne vs.<note n="f" place="margin">Rom 8. verſ. 28.</note> The Apoſtle ſaith that <hi>all things worke togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the good of thoſe that loue God,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Bernard. ſerm. de fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lac praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis vitae, &amp; in Pſal. 15. ſerm. 2.</note> which is ſo true, that eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the things which properly are not thinges but the corruptions of thinges, as griefe, ſickneſſe, death, and finally ſinne it ſelfe doe ſo. The latter may ſeeme ſtrange, and yet it is true, namely that even ſinne worketh for the good of the faithfull, yea ſinne is made a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine for ſinne. We know how foule a ſinne pride is, and how deepely it is rooted in our corrupt nature, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther incorporated into it,<note n="h" place="margin">Hier. ep. 30</note> wee had rather bee without golde it ſelfe then without pride and ſelfe liking.<note n="i" place="margin">Bernard. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>piſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 143<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> To doe greate workes and haue humble thoughts is far a harder matter then much faſting, long watching, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the like corporal afflictions. Nay to doe any good worke be it never ſo meane and not to glory in it, is a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue that is found but in few, and yet to be proud of well doing, is little bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter then ill doing. And<note n="k" place="margin">Auguſt de tempor. ſerm. 49.</note> ſome haue ventured to affirme that an humble ſinner is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one that is proud for doing good, and that God is more
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:102:52"/>pleaſed with humilitie in ill doing, then with pride in wel doing. At leaſt this we may be bold to ſay<note n="l" place="margin">Gregor. Moral. lib. 19 c, 12. &amp; 13.</note> that pride marres the luſter &amp; grace of our beſt actions and makes them meerely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable vnto vs, and they that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome their vices, by being prowd of it, are overco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e by that which they had overcome, &amp; foiled by their own victorie. We ſee then of what neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity humilitie is, without which all vertues are no vertues, and how abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable pride is, that in a maner tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all vertues into vices. Whence<note n="m" place="margin">Aug. ep. 52</note> S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> profeſſeth, that if <hi>he were demanded what were the firſt point of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie, he would anſwer humility, if what were the ſecond, he would likewiſe ſay hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, if what the third, his anſwer alſo ſhould be, humilitie,</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Cie. de o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. lib. 3.</note> even as the Orator being asked what was the firſt, ſecond and third point of eloquence, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſtill, <hi>vtterance.</hi> Now there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo effectuall to kill that mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of pride, and to breed this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vertue of humilitie, as ſinne it ſelfe, when God giues vs grace to bee humbled with the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.<note n="o" place="margin">Auguſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Civ. Dei. lib. 11. c. 14.</note> We may then be bold to ſay that it is profitable even for good men to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:102:53"/>fall into ſome manifeſt ſin that they might be diſpleaſed with themſelues, who fell by pleaſing themſelues. In a word the ſinne of pride cannot be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but by other ſinnes which makes vs aſhamed of our ſelues,<note n="p" place="margin">Ezech. 6. verſ. 9. &amp; 20. verſ. 43. &amp; 36<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> verſ, 31.</note> yea and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to loath our ſelues, and to bluſh to our ſelues, when ſometimes others commend and extoll vs, that are not privie to our faults. So by this means we are preſerved both from flattering our ſelues and alſo from applauding to others when they flatter vs, yea fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taking pleaſure in their iuſt praiſes,<note n="q" place="margin">Hieron. ep 32. Aug. ep 64.</note> which is exceedingly dangerous, &amp; yet almoſt impoſſible to bee avoided ſaving by this meanes. And as our ſinnes and ſlippes keepe vs in humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, ſo doe they alſo teach vs feare, care, and circumſpection, that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards we will not ſo eaſily bee over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken againe, ſo that we may well co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with<note n="r" place="margin">Bern. quo ſupra lit. marg. g.</note> S. <hi>Bernard, Doe not his ſinnes turne to his good, that riſeth from his ſinnes more humble, more fearefull, more carefull and warie then he was before? Doubtleſſe his very fall is happy that is taken vp by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie.</hi> This is the vnſearchable wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and ineſtimable goodneſſe of God to cure ſinne by ſinne, and to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:102:53"/>turne poyſon it ſelfe into a medicine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 9</hi> Conſolations againſt certaine circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſinne, namely long continuance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, before our converſion; and relapſe into it after our converſion.</head>
               <p n="1">1 Thus we haue heard what reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Chriſtian religion affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth againſt ſin, in reſpect of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance thereof. But now there are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine circumſtances of ſin which doe not a little aggravate the ſame, and wherwith the conſcience many times is much terrified. Which are princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally two, late repentance for ſin, and relapſe into ſin after repentance.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Touching the former, to weete late repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, there is no cauſe, why we ſhould be diſmaide therewith. For firſt we are to conſider, that although we liue an hundred yeares, yea many hundred yeares, if it could bee, which without extraordinary priviledge ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be hoped for, cannot poſſibly be: yet the diſtance of time betweene the day of our birth &amp; the day of our death is nothing vnto God.<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 90. v. 4. 2. Pet. 3. v. 8.</note> For as the Prophet ſaies, &amp; the Apoſtle fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him repeates it, <hi>a thouſand yeares with
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:102:54"/>the Lord are but as one day.</hi> Howſoever then to vs things are ſaid to bee done early or late: yet in reſpect of God nothing is ſooner or later, no time is long or ſhorte, nay no time is either paſt or to come, but al time is preſent vnto him. Let our care be that our re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pentance be vnfaigned, &amp; it ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be too late. Againe for our farther comfort herein, let vs obſerue,<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 20. v. 1.3. &amp;c.</note> that moſt divine parable of our Saviour Chriſt touching the laborours hyred by an owner of a vineyarde to worke therein, ſome of them early in the morning, ſome at the third howre of the day, ſome at the ninth, ſome at the eleventh, &amp; yet whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they came to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their wages, they that were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp laſt had as much as they that were intertained firſt. which inſinuats that ſo wee be brought to ſerue God truly &amp; faithfully, our late co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to his ſervice, ſhal no way preiudice our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, but that we ſhall be as well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, as they that bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> long hefore vs.<note n="c" place="margin">Epieur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Laert,</note> The very heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could ſay, that <hi>no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was too old to learne thoſe things which concerned the health of the minde:</hi> much more ſhould we reſolue that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is too olde to learne and practiſe thoſe
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:102:54"/>things which pertaine to his eternall happines, &amp; welfare.<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 11. verſ. 32.</note> Chriſt raiſed <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zirus</hi> our of his graue; eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after he had laine ſo long there that hee ſtunke: &amp; therefore can raiſe vs out of the graue of ſin, although we haue laine ſo long therein, that we ſeeme paſt recoverie, as the ſiſters of <hi>Lazarus</hi> imagined of their brother. Let vs therefore aſſure our ſelues <hi rend="sup">o</hi> that while wee bee yet in this world,<note n="e" place="margin">Cyp. cont. Demetrianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note> our repentance can never be too late, but that there is a paſſage from our mortal ſtroake to immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,<note n="f" place="margin">Hier. ep. 7.</note> And that we ſhould not deſpaire in this regard, God hath left vs a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table example<note n="g" place="margin">Luc. 23. v. 40.41<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.43</note> in holy Scripture, where we read that the penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t theefe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d preſent paſſage from the gibbet to heaven. Nay where God vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth the grace to repent truely, there may be a benefit in repenting lately, yea a double benefit, namely ferven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and conſtancie in the worſhip and ſervice of God Fervency, becauſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loſt ſo much time we ſhould la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to fetch it vp and recover it by diligence and induſtrie, &amp; thinke wee can never ſerue God enough, becauſe it was ſo long before we bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſerue him, whom wee ſhould<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> haue ſerved e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:102:55"/>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Seneca Nat quaeſt. l. 3. in praef.</note> And herein we are to imitate travailers, which by reaſon of ſome impediments and lets haue ſtaide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde their fellows: the later they ſet out, the faſter they travaile, and by haſte &amp; ſpeed make amendes for their ſlowneſſe and ſlacknes. So late con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion ſhoulde not diſcourage vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſerving of God: but encourage vs to ſerue him more fervently. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d advantage that may bee made of late repentance is conſtancie. And indeed this benefit doth ordinarily follow it. Many ſeeme to repent for ſinne be fore they know what ſin is, or at leaſt effectually apprehende the daunger thereof, and therefore commonly are ſoone drawne into ſinne againe, &amp; ſo drawne againe into it, as they wil ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver after be dravvne out of it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore never attaining to ſound repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, becauſe their repentaunce was too young, not repenting when they ſhould, becauſe they repented before they truely could. But co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarily they moſt loath ſin, that ſee their folly and madnes in ſerving it ſo long,<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 7.47.</note> and the more &amp; greater the woundes of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoule are, the more &amp; greater will her loue bee to Chriſt her heavenly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:102:55"/>Phyſitian. In a word<note n="k" place="margin">Sen. ibid.</note> as the very hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then hath well obſerved, <hi>The ſureſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage from vice to vertue is by the bridge of repentance;</hi> and we then moſt conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleaue to that which is good, when we haue beene ofteneſt, and deep lieſt ſtung by evill. Thus vvhen God giveth ſpirituall wiſdome to the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, his late repentaunce ſhall rather be adva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tageous, than da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable to him.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The ſecond circumſtance which maketh ſin to terrible in our apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion, &amp; indeed ſo dangerous in it ſelfe is relapſe into the ſame ſinnes after repentance. How great an evill this is<note n="*" place="margin">Chapt. 2. Sect. 9.</note> hath already in part been declared. But we may further conſider, that this is a ſtep &amp; degree to the feareful ſtate of thoſe, of whom<note n="l" place="margin">2. Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>the ſame is happened vnto them which is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to bee ſpoken in the true proverbe, The dogge is turned to his own vomit againe, &amp; the ſow that was waſhed, to her wallowing in the mire.</hi> We ſhould with feare and trembling thinke vpon that,<note n="m" place="margin">Mat 13, 43. &amp;c.</note> which our Saviour Chriſt delivereth in the Goſpell, <hi>that when the vncleane ſpirit is gone out of a man, if he returne &amp; enter into him againe, he bringeth ſeaven other ſpirits with him worſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> himſelfe, &amp; taketh ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:102:56"/>poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in him tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had before, ſo that the laſt ſtate of that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is worſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the firſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 But yet if through frailty we be overtaken even thus far alſo as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe into the ſame offenſes: yet muſt we not deſpaire by &amp; by, but there are ſome comforts, &amp; remedies left vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this ſo dangerous a temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p n="5">5 And firſt let vs conſider, that the worthieſt ſerva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God were not all togither free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this relapſe into the ſelfe ſame ſinnes.<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.8. &amp;c. &amp; 20.2. &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> twice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied &amp; diſclaimed his own wife, there by greatly engaging &amp; endangering her chaſtity, &amp; after a ſorte beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming a bawde vnto her; vvhich proceeded from infidelity, for that he could not reſt vpon Gods protection, but would provide for his ſafety by deviſes and ſhifts of his owne. And<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 26.6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> denied his Maſter Chriſt not once, nor twice but thrice, &amp; that every time in worſe ſo t than other, firſt by ſimple deniall, ſecondly by oath, thirdly by impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and curſing.<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 7.15. &amp; 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaies of himſelf, <hi>that which I doe, I allow not: for what I woulde that do I not, but what I hate, that do I,</hi> ſpeakes not of ſome one evill act, but of the whole courſe of his life, which argues
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:102:56"/>not only his doing, but his often do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what he would not, and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſundry times in the ſame things. But more manifeſt is that which hee teſtifieth of himſelfe<note n="q" place="margin">2 Cor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 12.7. &amp;c.</note> in an other place, <hi>that hee was vexed with a pricke or ſting in the fleſh, even the meſſenger of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that buffeted him,</hi> as he ſpeaketh, <hi>&amp; that he had prayed thrice to haue it taken away, but could not prevaile in that his ſuit,</hi> but yet received ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort againſt al da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger thereof. Here it is appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that the Apoſtle ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the ſamething, although he do not ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie what it was, &amp; it were fond curioſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie in vs to be inquiſitiue that way.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Furthermore moſt comfortable in this caſe is the doctrine of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt,<note n="r" place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. 18. v. 21.22.</note> where beeing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ked of <hi>Peter,</hi> how often hee was to forgiue his brother that offended againſt him, whether vntill ſeaven times or no, anſweareth him, <hi>that hee vvas to doe it not ſeaven times, but ſeaventie times ſeaven times.</hi> So<note n="ſ" place="margin">Luk. 17.4.</note> in an other place in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing his diſciples in general tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſame point hee ſaith. <hi>If thy brother ſinne againſt thee ſeaven times in a day; &amp; ſeaven times a day come againe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, &amp; ſay, it repenteth mee: thou ſhalt
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:102:57"/>forgiue him.</hi> Doubtleſſe hee that enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs to bee mercifull one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, although wee often commit the ſame offenſes one againſt an other, vpon acknowledgement of the faults and ſorrow for the ſame: will be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto vs vpon our repentance &amp; ſubmiſſion, although we often offend him in the ſame manner. He will not practiſe leſſe mercy towards vs, than he requireth that wee ſhould practiſe one towards another. Our mercie is but a ſparckle of his infuſed into vs by his ſpirit: and ſhall a ſparke doe more than the whole fire? ſhall there bee more in the ſtreame then in the fountaine, more in the river than in the maine ſea?</p>
               <p n="7">7 And here we are farther to note that the true nature of our iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſiſts not only in a general par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſins paſt, but in a particular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the pardon of ſin graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs in Chriſt to our particular of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted in the whole courſe of our life, and that there is place not only for our firſt repentance, but for dayly repentaunce according to our dayly ſins. And ſurely<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſat. 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Chriſt would not haue commaunded vs to pray for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:102:57"/>dayly forgiuenes of ſins, if he woulde not dayly forgiue them, not often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite vs to repentance, if he would not pardon vs vpon our repentance, and as<note n="u" place="margin">Ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul de paenit. ca. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> pithily ſaies <hi>God woulde not threaten him that doth not repent: if hee woulde not pardon him that doeth repent.</hi> This is the ſtate of a Chriſtians life<note n="x" place="margin">Auguſt. de Temp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erm. 47 &amp; G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eg. in Cant. c. 4.</note> that notwithſtanding their ſinnes, they continue righteous through the dayly forgiuenes of ſinne, and recaine their righteouſnes by beway ling their vnrighteouſnes, ſo it be vnder faith in Chriſt.<note n="y" place="margin">Aug queſt. Evang<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ib. 2. quae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. 33,</note> 
                  <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> is bold to ſaie, <hi>that Chriſt is then ſlaine to every man, when he beleeveth that be was ſlain.</hi> Thus ſaith for often woundes hath often ſalues, or rather one and the ſelfeſame ſalue, which beeing often applied is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to cure our often wounds. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs not be aſhamed to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to this remedie.<note n="z" place="margin">Bernard. ep. 112.</note> Let vs be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed that we ran away, but not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to returne into the fielde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and figh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> againe after flying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.<note n="a" place="margin">Tertul. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> poenit. ca<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 7.</note> Let it grieue vs to offende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; but not to repent againe: let it grieue vs to come in daunger againe but not to be delivered againe. When we are in danger let it g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vs to fal
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:102:58"/>ſicke againe; but not to bee cured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Indeed we ſhould deſire and ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iue not to ſin: but<note n="b" place="margin">Cypri. ep. 33.</note> as the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of happineſſe is not to ſin; ſo the ſecond is to confeſie our ſins, &amp; to be ſorry for them. And true ſorrowe for ſin in a manner maketh ſin to bee no ſin, as not only the Gentill ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">Sen. Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memn. act 2</note> in the Poet.<note n="*" place="margin">Quem poe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitet pecaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te pene eſt innocens.</note> 
                  <hi>He that is ſorry that hee hath done evill is almoſt innocent:</hi> but alſo<note n="d" place="margin">Tertull ad Senator. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tolat. Non erit in culpa quem poeniter an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te fuiſſe.</note> an ancient Chriſtian authour ſticks not to ſay; * <hi>He ſhall not be in fault, that is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie he hath beene in fault.</hi> Wherefore to conclude this point, let this bee our reſolution<note n="e" place="margin">Tertul. de poenit c. 7.</note> that howe often ſo ever we haue offended, yet there is place for reconciliation, and that God not only may be pacified by ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſubmiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and humiliation, but that hee is verie willing and deſirous it ſhould bee ſo, and that therefore<note n="f" place="margin">Epiphan. haereſ. 59. five lib. 2. Tom, 1.</note> 
                  <hi>While as yet we are in this wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ld combatting with ſin, there is a riſing after our falling, there is yet hope, as yet a ſalue, as yet time, for confeſſion, &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 10.</hi> Of the greatneſſe of Gods mercie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the greatneſſe of ſinne hath no propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:102:58"/>
               <p n="1">1 IF yet we deſire to be farther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted and armed either againſt the ſubſtance of ſinne, or thoſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances thereof, that ſo aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the terrour of it, we muſt laſtlie conſider the infinit greatnes of Gods mercy and goodnes, that needes muſt be of greater force to ſaue vs tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſins can be to condemne vs. Here we are entring into a ſea that hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tome, nor ſhoare. For as all other of Gods attributs are infinit, ſo is his mercy alſo; which that we may the better know, it is to be noted, that there are no qualities in God, but that all that is in him is his verie eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. God then is not accidentallie iuſt wiſe, mercifull, and the like: but eſſentially, that is, to ſpeake properly hee is not iuſt, but iuſtice it ſelfe; not wiſe, but wiledome it ſelfe; not merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but mercy it ſelfe. This ſhewes how great his mercy is, or rather it ſhewes it not, for what can ſhewe vs that which is incomprehenſible? But yet this in parte inſinuates the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Gods mercie, namely that it is as great as himſelfe, and that no mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vaile, ſith it is himſelfe. But firſt let vs
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:102:59"/>heare what himſelfe teſtifieth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that way that only is able per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly to know himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>The Lord,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 113. ver 8. &amp; ſeq.</note> ſaith <hi>David, is mercifull and gratious, of long ſuffering, and pienteous with goodnes, hee chideth not for ever, nor keepeth his anger alwaies, hee dealeth not with vs according to our ſinnes, nor rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs according to our iniquities, but as high as the heavens are aboue the earth, ſo much doth his mercie gue beyond them that feare him, as far as the Eaſt is from the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt, ſo far doth he remoue our ſinnes from vs, as a father hath pitty on his children, ſo hath the Lord pitty on them that feare him; for he knoweth whereof we are made, hee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth that we are but duſt.</hi> Here we haue not only a profeſſion of the greatnes of Gods mercy in expreſſe words, but alſo a liuely reſemblance thereof by moſt proper compariſons, yea moſt forcible arguments alſo and reaſons for proofe thereof, as God vvilling, ſhall hereafter be obſerved.<note n="b" place="margin">Eſai 49. verſ. 15.</note> Againe ſaith the Lord, <hi>Can the mother forget her young childe, and not haue pitty of the ſon of her wombe? but be it that a mother may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, yet will not I forget thee ſaith the Lord.</hi> And<note n="c" place="margin">Eſay 55. v 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.</note> in the ſame Prophet, to weete <hi>Eſay, Let the wicked forſake his evill waies,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:102:59"/>&amp; the vngodly his imaginations, &amp; retur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e vnto the Lorde, and hee will haue mercie on him, and to our God, for he is full of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For my thoughts are not as your thoughts nor my waies as your waies, but as high at the heavens are aboue the earth, ſo high are my waies aboue your waies, and my thoughts aboue your thoughts.</hi> And ſo<note n="d" place="margin">ſer. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> in <hi>Ieremie, If a man bee divorced from his wife, &amp; ſhee departing from him ſhall bee marryed to an other, ſhall he take her againe, ſhould not the land be defiled thereby? But thou haſt plaide the whore with many lovers, &amp; y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t returne to me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aith the Lord.</hi> And in<note n="e" place="margin">Ezech 18. ver. 23 31.</note> 
                  <hi>Ezechiell</hi> hee even mourneth for the follie and obſtinacie of his people, that woulde not returne vnto him and liue. <hi>Am I delighted with the death of a ſinner, ſaith the Lorde, and not rather with this that hee ſhould returne from his waies and liue? Why will yee die ô houſe of Iſraell?</hi> Out of theſe Scriptures &amp; the like we may gather many conſolations wherby to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the forgiueneſſe of our ſins. And firſt let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that Gods loue infinitely exceedeth any loue that is to be found in the creatures, being as farre aboue it as the heavens are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the earth, or the vtmoſt endes of the worlde are diſtant one from an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:102:60"/>And yet wee ſee that the loue which is in the creatures is of greate force, and produceth very ſtrange ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects; and ſpeciallie that loue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God here compareth his, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that of parents towards their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who loue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea tenderly loue them, even when they are vnworthy of their loue, and gladly embrace any ſubmiſſion from them.<note n="f" place="margin">Teren. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a. Act. 5. ſcen. 3. Propeccato magno pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cii ſatis eſt patri.</note> Even nature hath taught men to plead this, * <hi>That a father is ſatis fied with a little puniſhment for a great offence.</hi> Nay we ſee that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but loue their ſtubborne children, that refuſe to ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. yea that ſtand at open defiance with them, whereof the Scripture af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth vs a notable example.<note n="g" place="margin">2. Sam. 15 ver. 1.2, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> moſt vnnaturally rebelled againſt his father king <hi>David<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> after that hee had pardoned him for a cruell and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious murther; and ſought to depriue him both of crowne and life. For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in kings theſe both goe togither, vvho leaue to bee men when they leaue to be kings, &amp; can no longer hold their liues than they hold their ſoveraigne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty. Hee I ſay, vnnaturally rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt ſo kinde a father, and was vp in armes againſt him. And yet
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:102:60"/>ſee howe his father was affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him Having raiſed an armie to ſuppreſſe him,<note n="h" place="margin">Chap. 18.5. &amp; 12.</note> hee chargeth his two principall captaines that they ſhould deale gently with <hi>Abſalon</hi> for his ſake.<note n="i" place="margin">Verſ. 31.32 33.</note> And when afterwarde he had newes that he was ſlaine, he made moſt piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for him, crying out; <hi>My ſon Abſalon, my ſon, my ſon Abſalon, woulde God I had dyed for thee, would God I were in thy ſteed, ô Abſalon my ſonne, my ſonne.</hi> Thus nature forced him to loue even a rebellious ſonne. But moſt memora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble is that which happened in our age at <hi>Caſtillion</hi> vpon <hi>Loing</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Bodin de repub. lib. 1. cap. 4.</note> A father offering to giue his ſon a blow for ſome miſdemeanor, the ſonne ran him through with his ſword. Here the miſerable father perceiving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to death, never left cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after his ſon as long as he coulde crie, that hee ſhould flie and ſhift for himſelfe, leaſt iuſtice ſhoulde take hold on him. O admirable force of fatherly loue, that the father ſhoulde tender the ſonnes life that deprived the father of life. But God doth not only co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pare his loue to a fathers loue but alſo to a mothers loue, vvhich commonly is the more tender of the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:102:61"/>two, that ſex being paſſion arely indul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gent And of what force a mothers loue is even towards wicked and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratious children the ſame author in the ſame place ſpecifieth by the exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who having a ſonne that vſed her moſt outragiouſly, reviled her, beare her, threw her at his feete, and amongſt many other indignities committed one againſt her which I thinke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet to be mentioned in particular; yet would never complaine to autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of him: and when the magiſtrates of their owne accord tooke notice thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and holding the example in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lerable, convented him before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; gaue ſentence of death againſt him; the mother came crying and howling in moſt pitifull ſort, denying all the wrongs and outrage, he had done vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to her. And no marvell that the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents loue of their children is ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and vehement, ſith wee ſee howe ſtrong and ſtrange the affection of very beaſtes is towardes their young ones. <hi>The loue of their young ones,</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Sen ep. 75</note> ſaith <hi>Seneca, forceth wild beaſts to runne vppon the hunters iavelin or ſpeare;</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Nat. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes de ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. lib. 2.</note> and they vſually either recover them or die in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:102:61"/>attempting to recover them. Nowe theſe ſtrong inſtincts of loue in the creatures are derived from God, and infuſed into them by him. I ſpeake of the ſubſtance and ſoundneſſe thereof. For as for the irregularitie of it ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in men, it proceedes not from creation, but from corruption &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravation. But I ſay, this loue, yea this fervency of loue in the creatures comes from divine inſtinct. Now if God himſelfe infuſe ſo much loue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his creatures, how great is the loue that is in himſelfe? Doubtleſſe here that principle in Philoſophie muſt needs be verified, that <hi>that which makes another thing to be ſo or ſo, muſt needes bee more ſo it ſelfe.</hi> And therefore ſith God makes the creatures to loue ſo ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, doubtleſſe hee himſelfe doth loue more ſtrongly, as wee herd before out of Eſay that the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreſt humane loue was inferiour to his, even the loue of a mother towards her child, and that although a mother might forget her childe, yet hee would not forget his people. And no marvell that his loue is ſo greate, he being loue it ſelfe. For ſo wee finde in Scripture, not onely that God is loving,<note n="n" place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 16.</note> but alſo that
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:102:62"/>
                  <hi>God is loue.</hi> God ſaith not that hee is power, or iuſtice, although hee might truely ſay ſo, but when hee would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine himſelfe and tell what he is, hee makes choice of this attribute of loue and ſaith he is loue, which notably argueth how greate and ſtrong his loue is.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Furthermore we ſee by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer teſtimonies of Scripture, that his loue is tranſcendent, and aboue rule. He hath limited mans loue, &amp; mercie, and there are many caſes wherein men may not ſhewe mercy. The husband as we heard out of <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</hi> might not take his wife againe, that had plaid the whore, and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from him had coupled her ſelfe to another man.<note n="o" place="margin">1 Sam. 2. v. 37. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Elie</hi> the high Prieſt was ſeverely puniſhed for being too mercifull to his prophane ſonnes. <hi>Saul</hi> &amp; <hi>Ahab</hi> both loſt their kingdoms for ſhewing mercy to their priſoners contrary to Gods minde,<note n="p" place="margin">1. Sam. 15.</note> the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer to <hi>Agag.</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">1 King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0</note> the later to <hi>Benhadad:</hi> yea<note n="r" place="margin">Deut 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 6 7 8.</note> God made a generall law in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe tearmes, that <hi>parents ſhould not pitty nor ſpare their owne naturall children if they became Idolaters, and worſhipped ſtrange Gods, nor brother the brother, nor
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:102:62"/>husband the wife, no not his tenderly belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved wife; that their eie ſhoulde not ſpare them, but their hands ſhould bee vpon them firſt, to ſtone them to death.</hi> In theſe, and many other caſes me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might not ſhew mercy: and if they notwithſtanding would be merciful to others, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came cruell to themſelues, pulling down Gods vengance vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their own heads. Thus mans mercy is bounded, but Gods is boundles, and tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, ſo that he can and doth ſhewe mercy even in the caſes that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may not. As appeares by that before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged out of Ieremie, that although the huſband might not take againe his wife that had gone a who ring fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him: yet God was ready to receaue his people although they had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſpirituall whoredome, &amp; that with many lovers, that is, had defiled themſelues with many ſorts of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. And by this priviledge of vnli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited mercie God comforteth his Church and people<note n="ſ" place="margin">Eſay 55. v. v. 7, 8, 9.</note> in <hi>Eſaie,</hi> as we haue heard, chiding them for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie, that reaſoned thus, <hi>We haue ſo grievouſly ſinned againſt the Lord, that there is no returning vnto him, or hope of pardon. What?</hi> Saith God, <hi>Will you meaſure my
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:102:63"/>mercy by your mercy? Why, there is as great oddes betweene my waies, and your waies; my thoughts and your thoughts,</hi> that it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween my mercy and your conceipts of my mercy: <hi>as there is diſtance between heaven and earth.</hi> O comforte more worth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a thouſand worlds if there were ſo many. The Lorde doth not ſay, that his waies and thoughts of knowledge and wiſdome, but his waies and thoughts of mercy, are as far aboue ours, as the heavens are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the earth. And why then ſhould we doubt whether a mercy of ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent either could not, or would not relieue our miſerie?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Beſides this, let vs waigh how the Lord inviteth vs to returne vnto him, ſpeaking thus in effect to the ſin full ſoule; I knowe thou haſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſtraied from mee; I knowe thou haſt given mee too too many occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vtterly to caſt thee off, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of no ſubmiſſion: but yet returne to mee and thou ſhalt bee welcome. Thou haſt monſtrouſly defiled &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed thy ſelfe: yet waſh and purifie thy ſelfe, nay ſuffer mee to waſh &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thee,<note n="t" place="margin">Eſa. 1.18.</note> and if thy ſinnes were as purple, they ſhall be made as white as
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:102:63"/>ſnowe; and if they were as redde as ſcarlet, they ſhall be as wooll. Nether doth God deſire only that wee ſhould returne to him, but pittieth our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy when wee will not returne, as he ſaith in <hi>Ezekiel, O houſe of Iſrael, why will yee die?</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Luk. 19. verſ. 41.42.</note> And ſo Chriſt in the Goſpell bemoaneth the incorrigible perverſneſſe and frowardneſſe of the Iewes that would not imbrace mercy when it was offered vnto them, even weeping for the ſame,<note n="x" place="margin">Matth 23. verſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 13.</note> and breaking out into an affectionate complaint, ſaying, <hi>O Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, how often would I haue gathered thy children, even as a hen gathereth her chicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder her wings. but yee would not?</hi> Now hee that invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs to returne vnto him, yea that lamenteth our folly and frowardnes, that we will not returne; will he not receiue vs when we doe returne? Yes doubtleſſe. For ſure,<note n="y" place="margin">Tertul. de poenit. c. 8.</note> as an ancient Divine pithilie &amp; comfortably ſaith, <hi>God would not threaten him that repenteth not, except hee would pardon him that doth repent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 Moreover let vs out of the ſame places of Scripture obſerue that God doth not only promiſe to bee merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but alſo ſheweth reaſons, why he
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:102:64"/>wil be mercifull, nay in a ſort he muſt be mercifull. Beſides that which hath beene ſpoken hereof incidentally &amp; as it were by the way, namely that his mercy is not a quality in him but his very eſſence, and that there is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion betweene mans tendreſt mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy and his; it is more ſpecially to be conſidered, that he duly waigheth our caſe and fraile ſtate, namely that wee cannot but offend, &amp; that if he ſhould deale extreamely with vs, wee muſt needes be deſtroyed, but he graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beareth with our frailtie, knowing of what brittle mettle wee are made, and promiſeth<note n="z" place="margin">Eſay. 57. v. 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 16.</note> that <hi>although hee bee moſt high, and inhabit eternitie, yet hee will vouchſafe to dwell with the humble and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite, that he will not alwaies ſtriue, nor bee angry for ever, becauſe if he ſhould, every ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rit ſhould be overwhelmed and the ſoules which he had made.</hi> Thus he counteth vs no match for him, and thinks it no conqueſt to deſtroy vs, nay rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons this to be his honour and glorie to pardon and forgiue, and to ſaue where he hath iuſt cauſe to condemn. In a word, as a man diſdaines to ſhew his ſtrength vpon a child: ſo God diſdaines to ſhewe his ſtrength vpon
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:102:64"/>man. Which ſpeeches and the like plainely teſtifie howe eaſily God will accept of our ſubmiſſion, and what wrong we doe not only to our ſelues but alſo to him, when we imagine he is ſo ſevere and righteous that he can not or will not pardon our ſinnes, when we confeſſe them and are har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely ſory for them, whereas hee even delighteth to doe it, and takes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in it,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 51. v. 18.</note> according to that in the Pſalmiſt, <hi>that a bruiſed ſpirit and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heart are a ſacrifice to God.</hi> Thus God drawes arguments both from our imperfection, and his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, to perſwade vs of his readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to pardon, and to let vs ſee how eaſily it may be done.</p>
               <p n="6">6 To conclude looking backe to the foundation of his mercy, namely the incomprehenſible miſterie of the incarnation and paſſion of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt<note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 8. throughout</note> before declared, wee muſt needes ſee that his loue towards mankinde is infinit, and becauſe infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, therefore greater then our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſinnes.<note n="b" place="margin">Cyprian. ſermon de patientia.</note> Chriſts bloud waſhed even them that ſhed it, vpon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; and whom then can it not waſh? God would haue his owne and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:102:65"/>only ſonne to dy, that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might liue, &amp; was content that his bloud ſhould be our ranſome. Doubtleſle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">Auguſtin. Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine, hee that bought vs with ſo great a price, will not haue vs caſt away.</hi> Let vs then haue refuge to this infinit mercy of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and our ſinnes will va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away as a bubble. <hi>Our ſinnes,</hi> ſaith<note n="d" place="margin">Baſil in. regul. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract quaeſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.</note> 
                  <hi>Baſil, may both be meaſured &amp; numbred; but it is impoſſible that Gods goodnes ſhould be meaſured, or his mercies numbred.</hi> Let vs then reſolue,<note n="e" place="margin">Anſelm. in Meditat.</note> that, although our offenſes haue deſerved damnation, &amp; our repentance bee not ſufficient for ſatisfaction: yet Gods mercy is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then all tranſgreſſion, yea that <hi>as far as God is ſuperiour to man, ſo farre is our wickedneſſe inferiour to his goodneſſe.</hi> Wee may then with<note n="f" place="margin">Bernard. feria 4. heb<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom. poeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> reaſon thus; <hi>What, ſhall miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rie overcome mercy; &amp; ſhall not mercy rather conquer miſerie? Yes ſure</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Chryſoſt. proaem in E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ai.</note> 
                  <hi>our ſickneſſe hath meaſure; but the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine is without meaſure:</hi> and ſhal not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited goodneſſe prevaile againſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited wickedneſſe? or ſhal not a ſalue of infinit vertue, cure a ſoare of finite malignity? Gods mercy is a huge, yea a boundleſſe, and bottomleſſe ſea, and our ſinnes compared therevnto are but as a little ſparkle: now, ſaith <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:102:65"/>ſuppoſe that a little ſparkle ſhould fall into the maine ſea, could it abide there, would it not inſtantly be extinguiſhed, and never appeare more? Doubtleſſe ſo great a water muſt needes out of hand quench ſo ſmall a fire, yea a ſparkle onely of fire. Away then with deſpaire, and let vs aſſure our ſelues,<note n="h" place="margin">Gregor. Moral. lib. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cap. 11.</note> as <hi>Gregorie</hi> well ſaith, that <hi>deſpaire for ſinne is worſe then ſinne it ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 11.</hi> The Chriſtians peculiar comfories againſt death and the terrours thereof.</head>
               <p n="1">1 DEath beeing the greateſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall puniſhment for ſinne, it may ſeeme to ſome that I ſhould haue ſpoken thereof<note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 7. ſect. 2. &amp; ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> before, when I han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the remedies againſt all tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie evils which wee ſuffer in this life. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding I haue purpoſely, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerved the handling thereof vnto this place; becauſe it may bee obiected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our deliverance from ſinne by Chriſt declared in the Chapter next before going, that for al that the faith full die as well as other men, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:102:66"/>not poſſibly eſcape death, but muſt be and are ſubiect to the vniverſall lawe of inevitable mortalitie. Beſides, the chiefe and ſoveraigne remedy againſt this evill namely death is our delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from ſin, &amp; therefore I thought good to ſpeake of that before, that ſo I might be the briefer here, referring the Reader to the former chapter, for particularity, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenting my ſelfe heere with a generall repetition and application thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Firſt then as for death, we are to conſider, that it is chiefly ſinne that makes it ſo terrible vnto vs, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note n="a" place="margin">1 Corinth. 15. verſ. 56.</note> the Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>ſin is the ſling of death.</hi> Now, as wee haue ſeene at large<note n="*" place="margin">8.9.10.</note> in ſome former chapters, we are ſo delivered from ſin in Chriſt that it cannot hurt vs, nay is conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to our benefit and profit, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Death having her ſtrength from ſinne is not to be feared, ſith ſinne which is her ſting, is overcome. What need we feare the ſnake that hath loſt her ſting? Surely the ſnake that hath loſt her ſting can only hiſſe, and keep a noiſe, but cannot hurt: &amp; therefore we ſee that many having take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out the ſting will carry the ſnake in their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:102:66"/>boſomes without any feare. Even ſo although we carry death in our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, yea in our boſomes and bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els: yet ſinne which was her ſting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pulled out, ſhe can only hiſſe and ſtirre, ſhee may, and ordinarily doeth looke black and grimme, but yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not any way annoy vs.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Which will bee the more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, if we weigh that Chriſt our head hath conquered and quelled this Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant; ſo that none that bee his, neede ſtand in feare thereof <hi>Death</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">1. Corinth 15. v. 55</note> ſaith S. <hi>Paul, is ſwallowed vp in victorie;</hi> &amp;,<note n="c" place="margin">Revelat. 1. v. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt was dead, but now he liveth, and that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and hath the keyes of hell and death,</hi> as he himſelfe teſtifieth of himſelfe. Now he that hath the keyes of a place hath the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand of it; it is as much then as if it had been ſaid he had the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand of death, &amp; power to diſpoſe of death at his pleaſure. And will Chriſt that hath ſuch an enemie at his mercy let him annoy his deare friends, nay his owne members, and ſo in effect him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? No, no, he conquered death for vs not for himſelfe, ſith death had no quarrell to him; by his vniuſt death then hee hath vanquiſhed our iuſt death, as we heard<note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 8. Sect. 5.</note> before out of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin.</hi>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:102:67"/>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Bernard. ad mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es Templi ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>The death of Chriſt is the death of our death, ſith he dyed that we might liue, and how can it bee, but that they ſhould liue for whom life it ſelfe dyed?</hi> Surely death by vſurping vpon the innocent forſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her right to the guilty, &amp;<note n="e" place="margin">Hieron ad Heliodor.</note> 
                  <hi>While ſhee devoured wrongfully, was her ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 Yea, in that Chriſt hath vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed death, we alſo may be truely ſaid to haue vanquiſhed it, hee beeing our head, and wee his members, for where the head is a conquerour, the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers cannot be captiues.<note n="f" place="margin">Tertul de reſurre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. carms. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</note> 
                  <hi>Let vs then reioice, we haue already ſeyzed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heaven in Chriſt, who hath carried our fleſh thither in his owne perſon, as an earneſt pennie and pledge of the whole ſumme that in time ſhall be brought thither.</hi> We may then boldly ſay,<note n="g" place="margin">Auguſtin. in Pſal, 148.</note> 
                  <hi>there is ſomewhat of ours aboue alrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy;</hi> yea, the beſt part of vs namely our head, <hi>and are the members farre from the head?</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Idem in Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 88.</note> Yea, we may aſſure our ſelues, that, <hi>being members of ſuch a head. yea body to it, we are in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct where ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> head is</hi> For ſaith <hi>Auguſtin, this body cannot bee behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: but if the head triumph forever, the members muſt needes triumph for ever alſo.</hi> And that wee haue this benefite by Chriſts aſcenſion into heaven before
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:102:67"/>hand for vs,<note n="i" place="margin">Bern. ſerm. de eo quod legitur a pud Iob. in ſex tribulatio. nibus &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Bee it,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that only Chriſt is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into heaven: yet I trowe, whole Chriſt muſt enter, and if whole Chriſt, then the body as well as the head, yea every member of the body. For this head is not to bee found in the kingdome without his members.</hi> Hence it is that the Scripture ſpeakes of the faithfull as already raiſed from the dead, &amp; placed in heaven with Chriſt, yea as of them that ſhall not, nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not die, as<note n="k" place="margin">Ioh. 11. verſ. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee that liveth and beleeveth in me, ſhall never die.</hi> And<note n="l" place="margin">Ioh 5. v. 24.</note> againe, <hi>Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, verily, I ſay vnto you, whoſoever heareth my word, and beleeveth in him that ſent me hath eternall life, and ſhall not come into iudgement, but hath paſſed from death to life.</hi> And, <hi>Hee</hi> ſaith<note n="m" place="margin">Epheſ. 2. v. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Paul, hath raiſed vs vp togither, &amp; hath placed vs togither in heaven with Chriſt.</hi> He ſaith not, he will raiſe vs vp, hee will place vs in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with Chriſt: but he hath ſo raiſed and placed vs, which is ſpoken both for the certaintie thereof, &amp; alſo for the ſtreight vnion betweene the head and the body, by means whereof that which is already actually accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the head, is ſaid to bee ſo alſo in the body. In a word, the head being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue water, the body can never bee
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:102:68"/>drowned, although it bee never ſo much beaten and toſſed with waues. And thus much for our firſt and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall defenſe againſt death, the ſum whereof is this, that it is not onelie a weakeneſſe, but alſo a ſhame for the members to fear an enemy which the head hath already conquered &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued.</p>
               <p n="5">5 There are alſo diverſe other Chriſtian comfortes againſt death, which I wil briefly touch. And firſt, as we heard<note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 7. Sect. 2. &amp; leq</note> before, that all other evils of paine are to a Chriſtian chaunged into another nature, and of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments become favours and benefits: ſo is it alſo in this of death. For now it is not a toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods anger for ſin, but an argument of his loue and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; it is not properly death, but a bridge by which wee paſſe to a better life, from corruption to incorruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, from mortality to immortality, from earth to heaven, that is in a word, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vanity and miſerie, to ioy and felicity. And who would not willingly paſſe over this bridge whereby hee paſſeth from all cares and ſorrowes, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to all delights and pleaſures; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth all miſeries behinde him, &amp; hath
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:102:68"/>all contentation and happineſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him?</p>
               <p n="6">6 The Gentils taking it for grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that after death either wee ſhould be happy, or not be at all, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding that at leaſt death would free vs from all evill and miſery, therevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made litle reckoning of death, nay manie times voluntarilie procured their own death, and imbraced it as a rich treaſure, as wee haue<note n="*" place="margin">Chap. 4. Sect 3. &amp; Chap. 5. Sect 3.</note> already heard. But how fowly they were miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken herein, hath withall beene ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently declared. It is the Chriſtian only that enioyeth this benefite by death, namely the exemption from all cares and troubles, and an ende of all ſorrowes. Wherefore the death of the godly is called<note n="n" place="margin">Eſai. 57. verſ. 2. Dan. 12. v. 2. 1. Theſ. 4. verſ. 13.14. Revel. 14. v. 13.</note> in Scripture by the names of bedde, of reſt, ſleepe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> peace, and ſuch like. being all names of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite and commodity. How ſweet is peace to them that haue beene vexed with warres and broiles; how pleſant is the bedde, reſt, &amp; ſleepe to the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and thoſe that are overwatched? The labourer is glad when his daies work is done; the traveller reioiceth when he is come to his waies ende; the marriner and paſſenger thinke
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:102:69"/>themſelues happy whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they arriue in the harbour; and all men ſhun paine and deſire eaſe abhorre daunger and loue ſecuritie. It were madnes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a Chriſtian to feare ſo advantageous a death; and to wiſh for continuance of ſo wretched a life. I conclude this pointe with that elegant laying<note n="o" place="margin">Tertul. de teſtim. ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae. cap. 4.</note> of <hi>Tertullian; That is not to bee feared which ſets vs free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all that is to be feared.</hi> And indeed what weakneſſe &amp; folly is it to fear <hi>a ſuperfedeas</hi> againſt all the things which heare we do feare?</p>
               <p n="7">7 But the true Chriſtian hath yet a farre greater benefit by death. For it doth not only put an end to the evils of paine, but alſo to the evils of fault; not only to the puniſhments for ſin, but to ſinne it ſelfe, Now we haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten heard before, that the evils of fault are farre worſe then the evils of paine; yea, that the leaſt ſinne is more to be abhord and ſhund, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt puniſhment for ſinne. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come then ſhould death bee vnto vs, that endeth not only our ſorrowes, but alſo our ſinnes? As long as wee liue here, and beare about vs theſe earthly tabernacles, wee daily multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our rebellings againſt God, and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:102:69"/>ſuſtaine a fierce conflict, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al combat in our very boſomes, while<note n="p" place="margin">Galat. 5.17.</note> 
                  <hi>the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh, and</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 7.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>the lawe in our members rebelleth againſt the lawe of our minde,</hi> as <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>and leadeth vs captiues to the law of ſin which is in our members.</hi> O bondage of all bondages, to be in bondage vnto ſin.<note n="r" place="margin">Sen ep 37. &amp; 39.</note> The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that apprehended vice only as a morall evill, could ſay, that <hi>men beeing in bondage to their luſts were more cruellie handled by them, than any ſlaues were by the moſt cruell maiſters.</hi> Howe much more ſhould wee that feele ſin as al ſpiritual evill, and groane vnder the burden thereof, account the bondage there of intollerable, and worſe than ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the moſt barbarous Tyrant in the world? And how welcome ſhould he be that would ſet vs free from the ſame? Now it is death and only death that can doe this for vs, and indeede doth it for vs. What great cauſe them haue wee with all willingneſſe to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it?<note n="ſ" place="margin">Diogenes Laertius vit, Phil. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Zeno</hi> the founder of the Stoicall ſect helde it lawfull for them that had loathſome diſeaſes, vvhich were incurable to kill themſelues, that ſo they might be rid of them and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:102:70"/>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Con. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos in vita Titi Pomp. Attici. See alſo the like of Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus in Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca ep. 78.</note> 
                  <hi>Pomponius Atticus,</hi> &amp; others put it in practiſe. If they counted it a benefite to be delivered from a loathſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of the body by an vnlawfull and wicked death: we haue reaſon to think it a benefite, yea a ſingular benefite to be ridde of a loathſome and incurable diſeaſe of the ſoule, namely ſinne, by a lawful death, which it pleaſeth God to ſend vnto vs.</p>
               <p n="8">8 But death doth more for vs than all this. For it doth not only free vs from all evils, and from that evil of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, ſinne; but puts vs into actual poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of all good things, yea of ſuch good thinges as our eies haue not ſeene, our eares haue not heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are our harts able to conceiue; &amp; brings vs to that place, where if there were place for any paſſion, we ſhould be angry with death for not bringing vs thither ſooner. But I reſerue a more particular declaration of that point, vnto the thirteenth and laſt chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 12.</hi> Conſolations againſt the terrours of the generall iudgement.</head>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:102:70"/>
               <p n="1">1 THERE is yet an other thing which conſidered in it ſelfe is a greater branch and part of mans mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery in regard of paſſiue evils, than all the reſt; namely, the laſt and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall iudgement, where all fleſh ſhalbe arraigned before Gods Tribunall bar to giue an account of all they haue done, &amp; to receiue their recompenſe accordingly. The terror wherof I had rather expreſſe in<note n="a" place="margin">Anſelm. in libro medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta tionum.</note> 
                  <hi>Anſelmes</hi> wordes, than in mine own <hi>O hard diſtreſſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>on one ſide wil be our ſinnes accuſing vs, on the other ſide iuſtice terrifying vs; vnder vs the gulfe of hell gaping, aboue vs the iudg frowning; within vs a conſcience ſtinging, without vs the world burning. Which way then ſhall the ſianer thus ſurpriſed turne himſelfe? To hide our ſelues will be impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; to appeare will be intolerable.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal then ſhal miſerable man arme himſelfe againſt this ſo great terrour, &amp; danger? Surely our Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion affordeth munitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt this aſſault alſo.</p>
               <p n="2">2 And firſt that which hath beene ſpoken againſt the feare of death in the former chapter, ſerveth alſo here againſt the feare of the laſt iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:102:71"/>For that which made the firſt death ſo terrible and dangerous, the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ſecond death alſo ſo to bee, namely ſinne: and as deliverance fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne doth, as we there heard, free vs from al annoyance by the firſt death; ſo doth it alſo from all annoyance by the ſecond death, that is, eternal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation at the laſt iudgement. They that in Chriſt are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>querers over the firſt death; ſhall not, nor cannot bee conquered by the ſecond death: and<note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 2c. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>on thoſe that haue their part in the firſt reſurrection; the ſecond death ſhall haue no power,</hi> ſaith the ſpirit. That is, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not take hold on thoſe whom God hath gratiouſly called to the knowledge and love of his ſaving truth reveiled by the Goſpell.</p>
               <p n="3">3 But to come to more peculiar comforts againſt this matter of ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and amazement, let vs farther conſider that Chriſt had mercy on vs whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we were meere ſtrangers to him, nay even, <hi>when we were his enemies,</hi> as<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 5. v. 8.9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Paul</hi> well vrgeth, <hi>God herein,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>commended his loue towards vs, that when we were ſinners Chriſt dyed for vs: be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now iuſtified by his bloud; much more ſhall we be ſaved by him from that wrath.</hi>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:102:71"/>Note that he ſaith, <hi>from that wrath,</hi> that is, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wrath of the laſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <hi>For if,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>when we were enemies, we were reconciled vnto God, by the death of his ſonne: much more being reconciled, wee ſhall be ſaved by his life.</hi> Wee may eaſilie perceiue the force of the Apoſtles comfortable reaſoning: to wit, that ſith Chriſt died for vs when wee were ſinners, that is, nothing but ſin; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hee will ſaue vs being now righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in him: if wee were pardoned through his death, when we were eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; wee ſhall much more bee ſaved by his life, now that we are friendes. For how incredible is it, nay rather, how impoſſible, that he which pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth an enemy, ſhould condemne a friend? He loved vs, when wee bare the image of the devill: and will hee not much more loue vs now ſince he hath in parte repaired his fathers i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in vs, and confirmed vs to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. We were deare to him, when there was no iot of goodneſſe in vs: &amp; can hee reiect vs nowe that wee haue ſome good things in vs, although but weake, ſpecially hee himſelfe being the author and former of them by the grace of his holy ſpirit? And ſo<note n="d" place="margin">Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard. epiſt. 190.</note> 
                  <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:102:72"/>reaſons. For having ſpoken of our calling vnto the grace of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell, he inferres this; <hi>beeing thus puld out of the power of darkneſſe, I will not now feare to be reiected by the father of light, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing iuſtified freely in the bloude of his ſonne. Why it is he that iuſtifieth, &amp; who is it that ſhall condemne? Surely hee will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the iuſt, that had mercie on a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, &amp;c.</hi> Thus wee ſee he reaſoneth from that which GOD hath done for vs already, to that which he will doe; yea, in a ſort, muſt doe for vs here after. And we muſt all reaſon after the ſame manner, and ſaie everie one to his owne ſoule with<note n="e" place="margin">Auguſtin. in Pſal. 96.</note> Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, Thou waſt wicked, and hee dyed for thee; thou art now iuſtified, and will hee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 Moreover, to take away the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the laſt iudgement, conſider who ſhall be the Iudge: even Chriſt himſelf that was thy redeemer. And hovve canne wee feare ſuch a iudge? How happy in our caſe, that hee muſt be our iudge, that was himſelf iudged for vs? He is our husband and wee his wife; &amp; by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would the wife chuſe to be iudged, but by the husband, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by ſo kinde a husbande as wee
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:102:72"/>haue<note n="*" place="margin">Chapt. 10. Sect. 2. marginal. letter d.</note> before heard him to be, who ſheweth that favour that no husband doth: yea <hi>he is our head, &amp; we are his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> &amp; wil the head giue ſentence of conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt his own me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers? This in effect were to giue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelf <hi>He is our advocat and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> &amp; how happy would we think our ſelues if in cauſes touching this life our own atturney might be our iudg? <hi>He is now thine advocate,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 51.</note> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine that hereafter ſhall be thy iudge.</hi> Let vs then aſſure our ſelues, he vvill not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs, that hath already been, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for vs.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Yea, ſo farre of is it, that the laſt and generall iudgement ſhoulde be terrible vnto vs, that it ſhould rather miniſter matter of great ioy and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort vnto vs. And therefore our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt having ſet downe the chiefe ſignes and tokens that ſhould go before the day of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſaith to the faithful,<note n="g" place="margin">Luc. 21.28</note> 
                  <hi>When yee ſee theſe things begin to come to paſſe, looke vp, and lift vp your heads, for your redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion draweth neere.</hi> So that by Chriſtes owne exhortation in this place, when wee thinke vpon the laſt iudgement, we haue cauſe to reioice, not to fear;
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:102:73"/>to lift vp our heads, not to hang them downe. And that for ſundry reaſons, but I will ſpecifie one or two that are moſt materiall, &amp; fitteſt to cleare this truth.</p>
               <p n="6">6 And firſt, for as much as the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving of the world is for our ful de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liveraunce from the bondage of the world, the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of diſſolving it muſt needes bee comfortable vnto vs, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in it ſelfe otherwiſe terrible. Wee ſee that in particular humane iudgements, the things that are terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to malefact ours, are comfortable to good ſubiects; and that which ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the theefe, reviveth the true ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The maieſtie of the iudges, their ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let robes, whoſe very colour threate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s death, their guard that environ them with holdbards, yea the gibbet, &amp; the hangman are pleaſing ſightes to the good who knowe that all this is for their maintenance, and ſauegard, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they miſerably terrify the wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked, for vvhoſe deſtruction they are prepared. Even ſo the comming of Chriſt in maieſtie and glorie, the troupe and traine of Angels that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on him, the ſhrill ſounde of the trumpet ſummoning all fleſh to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:102:73"/>are before his iudgement ſeate, at this great and generall aſſiſes, and all other ſolemnities belonging to the pompe and magnificence thereof. wil cheere vp the faithfull; knowing that all this is to doe them iuſtice touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the wrongs and oppreſſions which they haue ſuſtained at the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of the wicked, and terrifie and daunt the wicked only, that now muſt come to an account for all their enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and outrages. And as it fareth with them that are narrowly beſieged in a ſtrong caſtle, when a puiſſant ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie is raiſed to reſcue them, &amp; draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth neere to the place, and is come within ſight, the neighing and tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling of the horſes, the glitring of the armour, the claſhing together of the weapons, the noiſe of drum &amp; trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet are moſt pleaſing vnto them, yea the very roaring of the canon is the ſweeteſt muſicke that ever they heard becauſe they knowe that all this is to raiſe the ſiege, and ſet them free: even ſo the faithfull, being ſtraightly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged in this world as in an impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable fort, by the fleſh, ſinne and the devill, when Chriſt ſhall come in the clowds with power and maieſty, when
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:102:74"/>the glorious army of Angels ſhall march onward with him as their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, when the laſt trumpet ſhall be ſounded, yea when the earth ſhal tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the ſea roare, the ſunne ſhall be darkned, the moon turned into bloud the ſtars fal from heaven, in a vvorde the elements diſſolved, and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens ſhall melt, and bee ſhriveled vp like a ſcroale of parchment, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhall reiolce at the ſight, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that al this is but to raiſe the long and grievous ſiege vvhich they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured in this world, &amp; to ſet them at liberty for ever; yea to put them in poſſeſſion of a heavenly kingdome where they ſhal raigne for ever in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable bliſſe.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Finally, that we may ſee vvhat folly it is to be afraide of this iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we muſt remember, that we our ſelues ſhall be iudges there. So <hi>Chriſt</hi> telleth <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 19.39.</note> that <hi>he and the reſt that had followed him in the regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that is, at the laſt iudgement, when the worlde ſhould be refined. <hi>ſhould ſit vpon twelue throans, &amp; iudge the twelue tribes of Iſrael:</hi> which being ſomewhat obſcurely vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, Chriſt there alluding to the preſent ſtate of things, the number of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:102:74"/>the twelue tribes of Iſraell, and of his twelue Apoſtles,<note n="i" place="margin">1. Cotin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> c. v. 2.3.</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth more cleerely, applying it in generall to all the faithfull vnder the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, affirming that <hi>the Saints ſhall iudge the world</hi> yea <hi>the Angels,</hi> that is to ſay, wicked men and wicked ſpirits. And hence<note n="k" place="margin">Tertul. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortat. ad Martyres cap. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> notably com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth and encourageth the Martyrs that were in durance daily expecting the Iudges comming, and to receiue ſentence of death. <hi>Perhaps,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>the Iudge is looke for; yea but you ſhall iudge your iudges themſelues.</hi> Were it not then great folly to feare that iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein wee our ſelues ſhall ſit as iudges, iudges, as I haue ſaid, of all wicked both men and ſpirits, that is, of all our enimies that haue oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs? For although Chriſt our head principally and properly ſhall be the iudge: yet we that are his members, ſhall haue a braunch of his authority, and ſhall be as it were, ioined in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion with him. Let vs not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feare this laſt and generall iudgement: the bench, not the barre, is our place there.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:102:75"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 13.</hi> The ioies of heaven, and glorious ſtate of the faithfull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death.</head>
               <p n="1">1 BVT that which moſt of all ſhould comfort vs againſt our miſery &amp; mortality here, and the terror either of particular iudgement by death, or vniverſall iudgement at the laſt day, is this, that not only all theſe cannot hurt vs, nay are made many waies pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitable vnto vs in this world, but that through them we paſſe to a moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſtate in the world to come, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency whereof requires the tongue and penne rather of Angels then of men to deſcribe it, or rather cannot be perfectly expreſſed by Angels the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. I muſt be content then darkly to ſhadow it out, ſith liuely repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of it is meerely impoſſible.</p>
               <p n="2">2 And firſt the benefits and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of this life although miſerable, as we haue heard, doe argue that a far better ſtate is reſerved for vs in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. We ſee that God even here on earth notwithſtanding our ſinnes,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:102:75"/>whereby we daily offend him, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeth vs many pleaſures, and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth vs not only with matters of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, but alſo of delight. There is<note n="a" place="margin">Paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> a whole Pſalme ſpent only on this matter, a Pſalme worthy to be writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in letters of gold in papers, walles, &amp; windowes, but ſpecially to be imprin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted in every godly heart for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable excellency thereof. <hi>God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Cyprian. de patienti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſaith <hi>S. Cyprian, the ſunne to riſe &amp; ſet in order, the ſeaſons to obey vs, the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to ſerue vs, the windes to blow, the ſprings to flow, corne to growe, fruits to ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, gardens and orchards to fructifie and aboud, woods to ruſtle with leaues, mead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes to ſhine with flowers &amp;c.</hi> And<note n="c" place="margin">Chry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt. de compu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ct cordis, lib. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> excellently handling the ſame point, further ſhewes that God hath in a ſorte made the night more beutifull then the day by infinit vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of bright, and glittering ſtarres, that hee hath beene more mercyfull to man then man would haue been to himſelfe, who of greedineſſe woulde haue overtoiled himſelfe, but that God made the night of purpoſe for his reſt; in a word he ſaies, and truely ſaies even of theſe earthly benefits &amp; commodities, that although we were
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:102:76"/>never ſo vertuous, nay if wee ſhould die a thouſand deaths wee ſhould not be worthy of them. And<note n="d" place="margin">Silv. Italic lib. 15.</note> the very heathen Poet conſidering this, could not chule but breake out into admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſaying<note n="*" place="margin">Quantas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pſe Deus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>tos gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravit in vſus Res homini plena<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit bona, gaudia de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra</note> 
                  <hi>O how many things hath God created for mans delight, and heaped ioies vpon him with a bounteful hand?</hi> And all this hath God done, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaies in the place before alleadged, to good and bad, to the harmeleſſe and harmefull, to the iuſt and vniuſt, to the religious and prophane, finally to the thankefull and vnthankfull. Whence wee may well reaſon thus, that if God deale ſo gratiouſly with vs on earth, hee will doe much more to vs in heaven; if he beſtow ſuch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits vpon ſtrangers, nay vpon eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, hee hath better things for his friends; if hee deale ſo bountifully with ſlaues, hee will be more bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full towards his ſonnes. For who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver vſed his ſlaues as well as his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Againe the excellency of his creatures argues a greater, yea incom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parably greater excellency in the Creatour,<note n="c" place="margin">Bernard. in feſto omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>vorum</note> as <hi>Bernard</hi> well obſerues: <hi>Thou wondreſt,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>at brightneſſe in
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:102:76"/>the ſunne, beautie in flowers, ſavory reliſh in bread, fertilitie in the earth; now conſider that all theſe are the gifts of God, &amp; there is no doubt, but he hath reſerved much more to himſelfe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath communicated &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to the creatures.</hi> Therefore when we meet with any thing that is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in the creatures wee may ſay to our ſelues, how much more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent is hee that gaue them this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie; when we finde admirable wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in men,<note n="f" place="margin">Seneca de beneficiis lib. 2. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9</note> how they rule al crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, by cunning overcome them that are farre ſtronger then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, overtake them that are ſwif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then themſelues, out runne the ſunne and moone in diſcourſe, telling many yeares before hand what cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they muſt hold when they ſhall be eclipſed, &amp;c. let vs ſay to our ſelues, how wiſe is that God that gaue ſuch wiſdome vnto men? When wee ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing ſtrong, as the <hi>Elephant,</hi> the <hi>Whale, winde, Thunder,</hi> &amp; the like, let vs ſay, how ſtrong is that God that made them ſo ſtrong; when wee ſee rare beautie in men or women, or moſt glorious colours in flowers, birds, &amp; other creatures, let vs ſay, how faire is that God that made theſe ſo faire;
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:102:77"/>when wee taſte things that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſweete and comfortable, let vs ſay how ſweete is that God that gaue them this ſweetnes? And from al theſe let vs conclude, that if the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures can afford vs ſuch delight, what will the creatour himſelfe doe, when wee ſhall immediately enioy his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in the world to come. Surely this world compared to the world to come, is but the gate houſe or porters lodge to the moſt magnificent pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and if the gatehouſe be ſo faire, how faire and glorious is the pallace it ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Moreover conſider what odd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s there is betweene Gods mediate pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and his immediate preſence, to enioie him in the creatures, and to enioy him in himſelfe. The creatures, yea the moſt excellent creatures, are as it were a vaile or curtaine drawne betweene God and vs. Nowe then when this curtaine ſhall be drawne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and we ſhall ſee God face to face, how glorious will that ſight be? Wee are here, ſaith<note n="g" place="margin">Bernard. de conſid.</note> Divine <hi>Bernard,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to the creatures, yea to the creatures inferiour to our ſelues: For the very ſunne, moone, and ſlartes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:102:77"/>they bee ſuperiour to vs in place, yet are they our inferiours in dignitie, and it is a kind of diſgrace for the ſuperiour to ſtande in neede of the inferiour, and yet from this neede are none of the ſonnes of men free, vntill they be brought into the gracious liberty of the ſons of God. Then indeede ſhall the glorified per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be no more beholden to the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For what need is there of any ſtaires to aſcend by, when hee is now ſet in the throane, there he ſees the word, and in the worde all thinges made by the worde, neither needeth to begge of the things that are made, the knowledge of him by whom they were made. Yea not only this curtain of the creatures ſhall be taken away, but alſo that of the word and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; For<note n="h" place="margin">Corinth. 13. v. 8.</note> as the bleſſed Apoſtle ſaith, propheſie ſhall ceaſe &amp; tongues ſhall faile, and knowledge ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed, that is to ſaie, knowledge gotten by outward inſtruction, and the miniſtrie of men, yea faith and hope ſhall reſigne their offices, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall we haue any more vſe of them, wee ſhall haue both immediate knowledge and actuall fruition of all
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:102:78"/>good things, yea of God who is good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe it ſelfe, and who there ſhall bee all in all to vs.<note n="i" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Wee ſee here in a glaſſe, &amp; as it were in a miſt or fogge, but there we ſhall ſee face to face, we know here but in part, but there wee ſhall knowe perfectly. The Apoſtle is bolde to lay that all the knowledge we haue here is as the knowledge and ſtuttering of a young childe, yea that his owne knowledge too was ſuch, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee were an Apoſtle, and a principall Apoſtle, and thereby inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuates that our knowledge here is as far inferiour to the knowledge which we ſhall haue there, as the knowledge of a childe that ſtuttereth, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not yet ſpeake plaine is to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the greateſt clerke in the worlde.<note n="k" place="margin">Plate in Phaed.</note> The very heathen thought this to be one great benefit, that men, ſpecially wiſe men had by death, that their knowledge was perfected in the other worlde, and that none could poſſibly attaine to perfect wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vntill they came thither. How much more ſhould wee count this an ineſtimable benefit, that in the life to come we ſhall haue the perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of heavenly things? Doubtleſſe
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:102:78"/>as farre as this wide worlde exceedes for light and comfort the narrow and darke wombe of the mother wherein the childe was wrapped before it was borne, ſo much doth that other world whereinto the faithfull after this life are received, exceede this world; and conſider then how great and glorious this alteration and change will bee. There ſhall bee tranquilitie without ſtorme, liberty without reſtraint, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety without loathſomneſſe, ſerenity without cloude, ioy without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, eternity without ceſſation.<note n="l" place="margin">Revel. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. verſ. 23.</note> This heavenly citty ſhall haue no need of the light either of ſunne or moone, for the glory of God illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates it, and the Lambe is the light thereof. And here,<note n="m" place="margin">1. Corin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 15. v. 28.</note> as the Apoſtle ſaith, God ſhall be all in all: meate to our taſt, beauty to our eies, perfumes to our ſmell, muſicke to our eares. what ſhall I ſay more,<note n="n" place="margin">Pſalm 87 verſ. 3.</note> glorious things are ſpoken of this citty of God but all that can bee ſpoken thereof is vnder truth, and<note n="o" place="margin">1. King. 10 v 7.</note> as the Queene of <hi>Saba</hi> ſaid of <hi>Salomons</hi> court, much more will the faithfull ſay of the Court of heaven when they come there, that the one halfe of the excellencie and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:102:79"/>glory thereof was not tolde vnto them. To the which place God for his Chriſts ſake bring vs, to whome with the holy Ghoſt, three perſons &amp; one God be aſcribed all glory, honor, and praiſe for euer and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>Chriſtianus Ouranopolitanus.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102:79"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
